最初  宇宙是一片黑暗\NIn the beginning, there was darkness,
紧接着一声巨响  混沌初开\Nand then, bang, giving birth
时间  空间和物质\Nto an endless, expanding existence
开始不断膨胀\Nof time, space and matter.
每天  我们都在解密这神秘莫测\NEvery day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
令人疯狂的极端之地\Nthe mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
宇宙\Nof a place we call the Universe.
这片广博寰宇\NThis cosmic world is unlike
不同于我们之前所见所学任何事物\Nanything you've ever seen or learned about.
银河系包含了宇宙中\NOur galactic neighborhood
最壮美绚丽\Nis home to seven of the most mesmerizing, violent,
最超脱尘俗的七大奇观\Nand otherworldly phenomena in the universe.
有一座神奇星球\NA stunning planet
其光环中的山脉\Nwhose iconic rings contain mountain ranges
可媲美阿尔卑斯山\Nthat rival the Alps,
一座闪闪的卫星上\Na shimmering moon
间歇喷涌出大量水和冰\Nwhere massive geysers of water and ice spew from its surface.
我们先去看一个超大火山\NScale a mega volcano,
然后穿越小行星带\Nthen zigzag through a family of Asteroids
去领略巨型旋风\Nbefore diving into the eye of a super-sized hurricane.
我们将见识太阳系中\NExperience the newest, most mind-blowing discoveries
最新奇刺激的发现\Nrevolving around our sun
体验其中的七大奇观\Nas we venture to the seven wonders of our Solar System.
本字幕由YYeTs人人影视翻译制作
翻译： 阿蘅阿蘅 QiWJ幽幽 陈易 Cath Angelica 小石头 \N 校对&时间轴： 泡泡龙 后期&特效： 丢丢&鱼骨头  总监： 丢丢
字幕转换、时间轴调整：liwei
宇宙
太阳系七大奇观
如果你觉得已看遍\NIf you think science has already uncovered every dangerous,
太阳系中危险神秘的奇异现象\Nstrange and extraordinary phenomenon under the sun,
那你大错特错\Nthink again.
我们正处在\NWe are right now in the midst
宇宙探索大时代中\Nof the greatest era of space discovery,
许多光怪陆离  奇妙万千的现象\NAnd many of the weird and wondrous things
就发生在我们身处的这个宇宙里\Nare happening right here in our own cosmic backyard.
太阳系真的是一个奇妙的地方\NOur Solar System is a really fantastic place.
我们已经发现了许多其他行星系统\NYou know, we've now found other planetary systems,
艾力克斯・菲利潘科\N加州大学  伯克利分校
但还未找到任何和太阳系相似的系统\Nand we've not yet found anything quite like our Solar System.
我们将开启一段神奇之旅\NYou've joined us on a magical journey
去探索太阳系\Nthrough the seven wonders
七大奇观\Nof our Solar System.
我们首先前往土星环\NWe first head for the Orbit of Saturn.
第七奇观  土卫二\NNumber seven, Enceladus.
2009年11月2日午夜\NIt's midnight, November 2, 2009.
NASA: 美国航天航空局
美国卡西尼号宇宙飞船\NNASA's Cassini spacecraft
正沿土星轨道飞行\Norbits the planet Saturn.
它拍摄到了土卫二\NIts cameras capture something bizarre
表面的奇异现象\Non one of its outer moons named Enceladus.
从地质学角度讲\NMost of the Solar System's moons
太阳系中卫星都是死寂的\Nare geologically dead,
而土卫二南极表面虽被冰层覆盖\Nand looking at the glistening, icy surface of its south pole,
看起来宁静如常\NEnceladus seems like a peaceful world.
突然毫无征兆地\NThen suddenly, without warning,
从地表裂缝中\Ngargantuan geysers of water and ice
喷射出大量水和冰\Neject from cracks on its surface.
土卫二是土星一个奇妙的卫星\NEnceladus is a fantastic moon of Saturn.
虽然体积很小\NThough it's relatively small,
但其火山活动与地球毫不相同\NEnceladus is different from the volcanism that's here on Earth
地球上的火山从地下喷射出\Nwhere hot magma, which is basically molten rock,
熔融岩石形成的炽热岩浆\Ncomes out from underneath Earth's surface.
土卫二喷射出的基本都是液态水\NEnceladus has water, basically, liquid water
喷射出后即冻结成冰\Ncoming out and freezing
因此也称之为冰火山\Nand so it's called Cryovolcanism.
卡西尼号宇宙飞船\NThe Cassini spacecraft flies directly
以1400英里时速穿过高达几百英里的\Nthrough the energetic plumes that blast hundreds of miles into space
喷射水柱\Nat 1,400 miles per hour.
土卫二着实吸引住了我们关注\NEnceladus has really caught our imagination recently
虽然卫星南极间歇冰泉非常普遍\Nbecause we see geysers coming out of the south pole.
但在太阳系外围  我们还从未\NWe haven't seen anything like that
劳拉・丹丽\N格里菲思天文台
在任何冰化卫星上发现此现象\Non any of the icy moons in the outer Solar System.
土卫二非常奇特\NSo something is going on in Enceladus,
我们想探究它如此活跃的原因\Nand it's active and we want to know why.
科学家计算得出土卫二南极\NScientists have counted at least 30 geyser jets
"老虎条纹"地质裂缝中\Nspouting from narrow geological fractures called Tiger Stripes
存在至少30处间歇冰泉\Nlocated along Enceladus' south polar region.
最新红外扫描地图显示\NA new infrared map of the area
此区域地表温度极高\Nreveals warm surface temperatures.
从地底喷射出的水蒸汽\NThe heat emanating from the Tiger Stripes
使"老虎条纹"常年保持高温\Nmay be due to the upwelling of water vapor that propels the jets.
有类似奇观的地方就是\NOne of the few other places to witness truly fascinating wonder,
地球\Nis on Earth.
在撒雪堆积的滑雪坡\NAt a freshly groomed ski slope
或是电影拍摄场地\Nor on a movie set.
看看这台造雪机器\NLook at this snowmaking machine.
就像土卫二上的间歇冰泉\NIt's like a geyser from Enceladus.
喷出的冰粒和水珠\NAll these ice particles and water droplets
遇到外界空气后冻结成冰\Nfreeze when they encounter that outside air,
膨胀的气体也会使水珠冷却\Nand the expanding gases also help cool the dropls
最后冻结成冰\Nand freeze them.
在土卫二上\NIn the case of Enceladus,
液态水在地底空间内加热\Nheated liquid water in a cauldron below the surface
随后从南极火山口喷涌而出\Ngoes squirting out through some vents in the south polar region.
水喷射出来\NAnd when that water comes out
进入外界低温环境\Nand encounters the cold surrounding space
就会冻结  形成雪花和冰粒\Nit freezes, forming snowflakes and ice particles,
就像这些造雪机造出来的雪一样\Nmuch like the ones coming out of this snowmaking machine.
所以我现在就像在土卫二上一样\NSo wow, I might as well be on Enceladus right now.
科学家认为土卫二上有2个内部热源\NScientists think there must be two internal heat sources
才会形成这种冰火山\Ndriving this icy volcanism on Enceladus.
第一个热源是放射性元素\NOne source could be radioactive elements
其衰变后会加热内部温度\Nthat decay and heat up the interior,
从而保持水的液体形态\Nthereby keeping the water in a liquid state.
第二个就是潮汐加热\NThe second could be tidal heating.
假设土卫二就像这个气球\NSuppose Enceladus is like this squishy balloon.
土卫二以椭圆偏心轨道\NNow Enceladus orbits Saturn in a slightly elliptical,
围绕土星运动\Neccentric orbit.
有时离土星较近\NSo sometimes it's closer to Saturn,
有时离土星较远\Nsometimes it's farther away.
当距离较近时\NWhen it's close to Saturn,
土星的引力\NSaturn's gravitational pull
对土卫二形成潮汐引力作用\Ncreates a greater tidal stretching of Enceladus
距离较远时就不会有这种现象\Nthan when Enceladus is farther away.
潮汐引力作用\NThat leads to a rubbing
使卫星内部失去平衡\Nof the interior materials
因此释放出能量\Nand a release of energy.
这种潮汐力\NThis tidal friction, as it's called,
促使土卫二内部融化\Nhelps melt the interior of Enceladus
从而使水保持液态或半液体形态\Nand keep the water in this molten or partly molten state.
另一个未解之谜\NOne mystery is,
就是土卫二地表下储存有多少水\Nhow much water actually exists beneath the surface.
这个小型卫星下\NCould the miniature moon
会不会隐藏着一个海洋\Nbe hiding an underground ocean?
我们推断地下有一个液态海洋\NWe infer that there is a liquid ocean
因为间歇性冰泉必须要有水源\Nbecause there needs to be a source of water to power these geysers.
海洋可能没有遍布\NThe ocean may not extend
整个土卫二的内部\Nunder the entire globe of Enceladus.
可能只存在于间歇冰泉所在的区域\NIt may be just beneath these regions where the geysers are going off,
格瑞格・拉夫林\N加州大学  圣克鲁兹分校
但肯定的是\Nbut there has to be
土卫二冰层下应存在\Na significant reservoir of liquid water
一个重要的"地下水库"\Nbeneath the surface of Enceladus.
如果土卫二地表下真的存在液态水\NIf liquid water exists beneath the surface,
其中可能蕴含着大量有机分子\NIt could be teeming with organic molecules.
有机分子以及适宜温度\NThese, along with relatively warm temperatures,
都是创造生命的重要因素\Nare the essential ingredients for creating life.
如果能在土卫二地表下\NIt would be incredible
发现原始生命\Nif we were to find life, primitive life,
那将太不可思议了\Nunderneath the surface of Enceladus.
我们并不指望出现类人生物\NWe don't expect complex creatures such as ourselves
或者兔子乌龟等高等生物\Nor rabbits or turtles,
但哪怕只是原始菌类或是微生物\Nbut even primitive bacterial or microbial life,
此类能够在地球上独立存活的生命\Nindependent of life on Earth
就算是有史以来最伟大的发现了\Nwould be one of the greatest discoveries ever.
土卫二运行轨道\NEnceladus actually orbits
其实就是太阳系又一大奇观\Nwithin another wonder of the Solar System.
第六奇观  土星环  \NNumber six... The Rings of Saturn
土星环被发现后\NThe Rings named in alphabetical order
字母表顺序加以排序\Nas they were discovered,
它是宇宙中最绚丽的景象之一\Nare among the most dazzling sights in the sky.
旅行者号飞船对土星的第一次探测\NThe Voyager spacecraft first visited Saturn
已是很久前的事了\Nquite a while ago,
现在看到卡西尼号飞船提供的新影像\Nand now with the new images provided by Cassini.
艾米・梅泽\N美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
像用3D眼镜看的一样真切\NIt's like putting on a pair of 3D glasses
我们首次细致详尽的看清\Nfor the first time to be able to see with great detail
土星光环里到底有什么\Nwhat's inside Saturn's rings.
据估计  七条大光环中\NAmong the seven main rings,
有数千层小环环绕着这个气态行星\Nit's estimated that the gaseous planet has thousands of ringlets
其中包含有三十五万万亿吨的冰和尘埃\Ncomprised of 35 trillion-trillion tons of ice and dust,
大约是地球水\Ncontaining roughly 26 million times
总重量二千六百万倍\Nthe amount of water on Earth.
它们的起源\NYet their origin
也困扰了科学家们近几个世纪\Nhas eluded scientists for centuries.
我们无从知晓这些光环起源\NWe really don't know their origin.
也许由于土星重力作用\NThey may consist of material
使它们无法相互撞击\Nthat never had a chance to form into a moon
以形成卫星\Nbecause of gravitational influences of Saturn itself.
又或者它们就是卫星\NOr maybe, they're a moon
由于太靠近土星而破裂\Nthat wandered too close to Saturn and got broken up,
被土星的潮汐引力作用打的支离破碎\Nshattered by the tidal gravitational effects of Saturn.
甚至可能是一颗彗星\NOr possibly even,
运动过于靠近土星\Na comet came in too close to Saturn
受土星巨大潮汐引力作用\Nand got tidally disrupted
从而土崩瓦解 \Nby Saturn's immense gravitational field.
更加引人注目的是\NWhat's even more remarkable
科学家统计出\Nis that scientists have counted
土星环中还隐藏着62颗卫星\N62 moons embedded in Saturn's rings.
最新影像资料表明这些卫星\NNew images indicate that these tiny satellites
使光环更加光彩照人\Nhave taken the rings to new heights.
2009年8月11日\NAugust 11, 2009.
一张罕见土星昼夜平分的照片中\NA rare equinox photo of Saturn
土星光环\Nshows her rings
侧向反射了太阳光\N"edge on" to the sun.
这幅照片揭开了一个惊人的事实\NThe image unveils a shocking fact:
曾一度被认为\NThe bright bands that
固态平整的光环\Nonce appeared to be solid and flat,
土星F环中细小波段
事实上还包含着山脊\Nactually contain ridges,
从几英尺一直延伸向高耸的山脉  \Nspanning from a few feet to mountain ranges
山脉
其高度比阿尔卑斯山还要高\Ntaller than the Alps.
通过地球上的望远镜\NWhen you look at Saturn's rings
观察土星环时\Nfrom a telescope on Earth,
它们看起来光滑而普通\Nthey look completely smooth and featureless.
但现在所看到的那些区域\NBut now we see that there are regions
土星F环中细小波段
是由光环粒子堆砌而成\Nwhere the ring particles are piled up into,
你可以称之为"山"\Nwhat you could call mountains,
山脉
高度可达数英里\Nwhich can be several miles high.
但这些高峰是怎么形成的呢\NBut how are these mile-high mountains formed?
美国卡西尼号太空船\NNASA's Cassini mission
成功捕捉到环内卫星\Nactually captured images of embedded moons
在土星环中运行\Nsweeping through Saturn's rings
使得光环扭曲不平\Ncausing them to twist and ripple
从而形成百变造型的影像\Ncreating ever-changing patterns.
在土星A环\NIn Saturn's "A" Ring,
即土星最外层主光环中\Nthe outermost of the large bright rings,
土卫三十五距离土星环垂直距离\Nthe moon Daphnis has carved a vertical peak,
土卫三十五
土星A环
垂直顶点
超过两点五英里\Nwhich is over 2 1/2 miles high.
卫星在运行过程中\NThe moons are interacting with Saturn's rings, in such a way,
克利福德・约翰逊\N南加州大学
与土星环之间的相互作用\Nas to either pull material
可以将物质排斥远离光环\Nslightly above the ring or below the ring
也可吸引入光环\Nas the moon goes round,
因为其运行轨道和光环自身轨道不太一致\Nbecause its orbit doesn't quite match that of the ring itself.
环绕着土星的光环\NThe ring system surrounding Saturn
堪称壮丽之景\Nis a spectacular sight.
但在临近星球上\NBut on a neighboring planet,
却又是另一番景象\Nthere's a very different scene,
巨大的让人难以置信的景象\None almost too monstrous to believe.
这在我们七大奇观中\NIt's number five in our countdown
排名第五\Nof the seven amazing wonders,
这是个超级旋风圈\NA raging storm,
它几乎可以圈下三个地球\Nthat's nearly three times the size of Earth.
我们将继续\NAs we continue our countdown
探索太阳系七大奇观\Nof the seven wonders of our Solar System,
我们已经探索过了第七奇观  土二卫\NWe leave behind number seven, Enceladus
和第六奇观  土星环 \Nand number six, The Rings of Saturn.
下面我们冲击\NWe now blast off
第五奇观\Nto number five,
木星大红斑\NJupiter's Great Red Spot.
这个超级风暴\NThis mother of all storms
足以圈下三个地球\Nis about three times the size of Earth.
我们还无法探知\NWe don't know exactly
大红斑是如何形成的\Nhow the Red Spot formed.
劳拉・丹丽\N格里菲思天文台
自人类观测开始它就已经存在了\NIt's been there as long as we've been looking,
可以上溯至十七世纪五十年代\Nas far back as the 1650s.
所以说在我们对其探索研究之前\NSo it was there before we started
它就存在了\Nreally paying attention.
大红斑\NThe Great Red Spot
事实上是种远古风暴\Nis actually an ancient storm
它已猛烈的旋转了几个世纪\Nthat's been spinning wildly for centuries.
这个巨型的漩涡\NThe super-sized vortex
高耸于木星云层之上五英里处\Ntowers five miles above the planet's cloud tops
但低于地球上任何风暴系统\Nand dwarfs any storm system on Earth.
据推测  木星大红斑内\NThe 400-mile-an-hour winds
风速达到了四百英里每小时\Nmeasured in Jupiter's Great Red Spot
比地球上最强劲龙卷风\Nare faster than some of the most powerful winds
艾米・梅泽\N美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
的速度还要快\Nmeasured in tornadoes here on Earth.
然而地球上的龙卷风\NYet, tornadoes on Earth only last,
仅仅持续十几分钟\Nmaybe a few tens of minutes
至多几个小时\Nor at most a couple of hours,
但是木星大红斑\Nwhereas Jupiter's Great Red Spot's
已经猛烈的运动了至少四百年\Nbeen going strong for at least 400 years,
而且大小相当于三个地球那么大\Nand it's three times the size of Earth.
你一定不想困进去吧\NNow that's one storm you don't want to get caught in.
地球南半球大多数热带风暴\NMost tropical storms in Earth's southern hemisphere
是和地球一样顺时针旋转的\Nspin clockwise as our planet rotates.
但是木星大红斑的运行轨道\NBut on Jupiter, the Great Red Spot
却与众不同\Nfollows an unearthly path.
木星大红斑\NThe Great Red Spot,
位于木星南半球\Nwhich is in Jupiter's southern hemisphere,
是逆时针旋转的\Nrotates counterclockwise.
艾力克斯・菲利潘科\N加州大学  伯克利分校
这属于反气旋\NIt's anticyclonic,
这是因为木星上是高气压系统\Nand that's because it's a high pressure system,
不像地球上的\Nunlike the low pressure systems here on Earth,
常伴随有风暴的低气压\Nassociated with storms.
因此高气压中的气流\NSo when you have a high-pressure system,
方向也就自然而然的\Nthe airflow is naturally
与低气压系统的方向相反了\Nthe opposite to that of a low-pressure system.
这个远古风暴团的起源\NThe origin of this long-lived storm
使天文学家们深表疑惑\Nhas baffled astronomers.
但现在  这个风暴团的神秘面纱\NBut now, science may be on the verge
即将被揭开\Nof unraveling its stormy secrets.
哈勃太空望远镜\NThe Hubble space telescope
近日拍下了木星上三个\Nrecently snapped images of three smaller storms
被称为白斑的小型风暴团的图像\Non Jupiter called white spots.
白斑
三年后\NWithin three years,
这三个白斑相互融合\Nthe three white spots merged
形成一个与地球大小相同的风暴团\Nto form one Earth-size storm.
然后  出乎所有人预料\NThen, the unexpected happened.
仅过了一周\NOver the course of only about a week,
风暴团就从白色转变成亮红色\Nthe storm turned from white to bright red.
我们称之为椭圆二号\NIt's now known as Oval BA
有时也称为小红斑\Nor sometimes Red Junior.
小红斑
它为何会变红\NWhy it turned red
又是如何变红的\Nand exactly how that happened
现在还无从知晓\Nis still a mystery.
现在天文学家怀疑类似的合并\NAstronomers now suspect a similar merger
可能就是大红斑的成因\Nmay have also created the Great Red Spot.
这过程与小红斑相似\NAnd like red junior,
猛烈的风暴团最初呈现白色\Nthe ferocious storm may have originally been white.
但随着它的速度加快\NBut as its speed grew faster,
它开始把来自木星大气层深处的\Ni began dredging up material
一些物质吸收上来\Nfrom deep in Jupiter's atmosphere.
其中一种\NOne of the compounds
可能是硫的某种化合物\Ncould actually be a form of sulfur.
我们还不完全清楚\NWe don't fully understand
格里・朗林\N加州大学  圣克鲁斯分校
大红斑为何成砖红色\Nwhy the red spot has its characteristic Brick red color,
也许是其中的化合物\Nbut probably there are chemical compounds
与阳光产生反应\Nwhich are reacting with the sunlight
从而形成了这种颜色\Nand are giving it this color.
天文学家一直在密切关注大红斑\NAstronomers have been closely monitoring the Great Red Spot,
在最近十年里\Nand in the last decade
他们观测到一个惊人变化\Nthey have detected an astonishing change.
我们观测到大红斑一直在萎缩\NWe've been watching the Great Red Spot shrink,
而且变得越来越园\Nand actually become rounder for some time now.
谁知道它会不会再存在四百年\NWho knows if it's going to persist for another 400 years
或许会完全消失\NOr maybe disappear entirely.
大红斑是太阳系中\NThe Great Red Spot is by far
迄今为止最大的风暴团\Nthe biggest storm in our Solar System.
离开木星之后\NBut after leaving Jupiter,
我们向太阳的方向\Nwe head about 200 million miles
继续前进两亿英里\Nin the direction of the sun,
与另一奇观\Nand have a close encounter
来一次亲密接触\Nwith another barely believable wonder.
第四奇观\NNumber four,
小行星带\Nthe Asteroid Belt.
科学家们希望了解更多\NScientists want to know more
关于这片小行星堆的起源\Nabout the origin of this cosmic junkyard of wayward debris,
这些碎片在太阳系形成伊始就存在了\Nwhich is left over from the formation of the Solar System.
很长一段时间内\NFor a long time
我们都以为\Nwe thought that, maybe, there had been
是某颗星球爆裂形成的\Na planet there that got pulverized,
是某场大灾难的遗迹\Nqnd we were just seeing the debris of some major catastrophe.
我们现在逐渐意识到\NBut we pretty much now realize
在那片区域不可能存在行星\Nthat a planet never was able to form there.
来自木星和其它星球的引力\NThe gravitational pull from Jupiter and the other planets
不可能让物质合成新行星\Njust made it impossible for material to coalesce into a planet.
在这片一亿英里宽的小行星带中\NWe traverse through 100 million miles of rocks,
有的小行星直径只有几英尺\Nsome as small as several feet,
有的直径比城市还大\Nothers bigger than cities.
这片区域可能含有数百万的小行星碎片\NThe belt probably contains millions of rocky pieces.
然而  如果所有的小行星\NYet, if all the asteroids
被压缩成一个整体的话\Nwere condensed into one boulder,
可能比月球还小\Nit would be smaller than our Moon.
研究这些小行星\NWe can start to learn more about
有助于帮我们了解\Nthe history of our Solar System
太阳系的起源\Nby studying the small bodies in our Solar System: the Asteroids.
我们希望了解它们是如何运行的\NWe'd like to know how they moved around,
如何受巨大行星影响\Nhow were they affected by the giant planets,
还有它们最终命运会如何\Nand what is their ultimate fate?
会变成什么形态\NWhat will happen to them?
陨石\NMeteorite!
商业电影中小行星带被描绘成\NPopular movies have portrayed the Asteroid Belt
宇宙陨石集中地\Nas a cosmic obstacle course,
在这里太空船需要闪避巨大陨石\Na place where spaceships dodge enormous boulders
陨石在坠入大气撞击地球之前\Nthat constantly collide and jostle for position
会不断互撞而争夺轨道\Nbefore hurtling down from space to destroy planet Earth.
但好莱坞电影描述的正确吗\NBut has Hollywood gotten it wrong?
小行星带有多么拥挤\NHow congested is the Asteroid Belt?
这是一位观众最想知道的宇宙秘密\NThat's what one viewer wanted to ask the universe.
密苏里州肯萨斯市的乔・T.向我们发来短信\NSo Joel T. From Kansas City, Missouri texted us...
电影是否准确反映出小行星带真实模样
感谢乔的提问\NThanks for the question, Joel.
我知道这有点震惊\NI know this is a bit shocking,
但大多数商业电影\Nbut the Asteroid Belt hasn't always been portrayed
对小行星带的描绘有严重偏差\Nterribly accurately in most blockbuster movies.
如果你在太阳系小行星带中\NIf you were orbiting an asteroid
随轨道运动\Ninside our Solar System's Asteroid Belt,
你无法察觉\NYou wouldn't be able to see
这些坑坑洼洼的巨型小行星\Nbig cratered surfaces of other asteroids
向你飞来\Nflying right next to you.
事实上  它们看上去\NIn fact, they probably look
就像是星星点点的灯火\Njust like distant points of light.
因为小行星带中绝大多数小行星\NThat's because the average separations
相互之间平均距离\Nbetween most asteroids in the Asteroid Belt
远远超出它们的实际大小\Nare much larger than their actual sizes.
所以它们看起来非常渺小\NSo they'd really just look like dots.
宇宙秘密
事实上  两颗小行星之间平均距离\NIn fact, an average distance
大约一百万英里\Nbetween two asteroids can be one million miles.
然而在这些奇形怪状的陨石中\NHowever, among this spacious sea of odd-shaped rocks,
也存在一个圆球形天体\Nexists a round ball.
谷神星是太阳系中最大的小行星\NCeres is the biggest asteroid in the Solar System.
这块直径六百英里的巨型陨石\NThe awesome 600-mile wide rock
占小行星带总质量的四分之一\Ncontains a fourth of the entire mass of the Asteroid Belt.
小行星带中大多数小行星\NMost asteroids in the Asteroid Belt
都成块状\Nare lumpy shaped,
有点像土豆\Nkind of like potatoes,
但谷神星不同\Nbut Ceres is different.
事实上  它非常庞大  拥有足够质量\NIt's actually big enough to have enough mass,
与重力\Nto have enough gravity,
使其成圆形\Nto crush itself into a round shape.
鉴于它独特的圆形特征\NBecause of its spherical shape,
谷神星升级了\Nceres was upgraded.
最近科学家们把它列为矮行星\NScientists recently listed it as a Dwarf Planet,
和冥王星的分级一样\Nthe same designation given to Pluto.
现在人们的观点是  它的规模太小\NThe modern view of Ceres is that it's not big enough
还不足以称之为星球\Nto be called a genuine planet,
但其质量足够大\Nbut it is big enough for it to have formed
以形成近球状外形\Na roughly spherical shape,
但还不足以成为一颗真正的星球\Nbut not big enough to be a true planet.
这个第四奇观\NThis fourth wonder
不仅是太阳系形成初始\Nnot only holds unique artifacts
就遗留下来的独特产物\NfFrom the formation of our Solar System,
更是潜在大规模杀伤性武器\Nit also harbors potential weapons of mass destruction.
许多小行星脱离了\NMany asteroids have escaped
小行星带的束缚\Nthe confine of the Asteroid Belt.
某个时候\NAnd at any moment,
这些离群的太空陨石\None of these rogue space rocks
可能会导致悲剧重演\Ncould repeat history,
没人能存活下来\Nand no one will live to talk about it.
目前为止  \NSo far,
我们已经领略了太阳系\Nour journey through the seven wonders
七大奇观之中的\Nof the Solar System has taken us
土卫二间歇冰泉\Nto the geysers of Enceladus,
土星环\Nthe Rings of Saturn
以及木星大红斑\Nand the Great Red Spot on Jupiter.
现在  我们继续探索太阳系第四大奇观\NNow, we continue to travel through the fourth of our wonders,
小行星带\Nthe Asteroid Belt.
这些远古遗物曾被搬上大银幕\NThis band of leftover debris has even made it to the big screen,
最令好莱坞着迷的\Nand the rocks Hollywood is obsessed with the most
是那些脱离小行星带\Nare those that escape the Asteroid Belt
撞击地球的天外陨石\Nand head for planet Earth.
近地天体是指\NNear-Earth Objects or NEOs
几乎每天都光临地球的\Nare cosmic rocks like asteroids or comets,
外太空岩石  例如小行星或者彗星\Nwhich strike Earth almost every day.
我们确实对近地天体很感兴趣\NWe're really very interested in Near-Earth Objects,
关注那些穿过地球公转轨道的天体\Nobjects that pass across the orbit of the Earth around the sun
因为它们撞击地球的几率非常大\Nbecause occasionally they can and do collide with the Earth,
艾力克斯・菲利潘科\N加州大学  伯克利分校
如果足够大  则可能对地球造成大面积破坏\Nand if they're big enough they can cause vast destruction here on Earth.
2010年4月14日\NOn April 14, 2010,
有镜头捕捉到一直径三英尺的小行星\Ncameras caught sight of a 3-foot fiery asteroid
从美国中西部天空呼啸划过\Nstreaming over the Midwestern United States.
幸运的是  在它撞到地面前\NFortunately, the cosmic rock broke into tiny pieces
就已碎裂成小块\Nbefore hitting the ground.
但在过去\NBut in the past,
美国  亚利桑那州
小行星撞击曾形成巨大陨坑\Nlarge asteroid impacts have created gigantic craters,
澳大利亚西部
加拿大  魁北克
甚至导致了大规模物种灭绝\Nand even triggered mass extinction events
比如导致恐龙灭绝的希克苏鲁伯小行星\Nlike the Chicxulub asteroid that killed off the dinosaurs.
在过去的十多亿年中\NOver the last billions of years,
地球被大小不一的小行星撞击过无数次\NEarth has been hit many times by asteroids of various sizes.
大约6500万年前\NThe impact that occurred roughly 65 million years ago
格瑞格・拉夫林\N加州大学  圣克鲁兹分校
一颗直径大约大约六英里的的小行星\Nthat perhaps wiped out the dinosaurs
撞向了今日墨西哥的区域\Nwas an example of something that was about six miles across
促使恐龙灭亡\Nthat slammed into, what is now Mexico,
对全球造成了难以想象的影响\Nand caused huge global ramifications for the Earth.
目前  一系列最新太空研究\NA number of new space surveys are currently tracking
正在追踪\Nall Near-Earth Objects
所有足以摧毁一座现代城市的近地天体\Nthat are large enough to destroy a modern city,
其中一些甚至会导致全球性大灾难\Nor even worse, ignite a global catastrophe.
我们已经追踪了所有直径超过一英里\NWe know of most of the objects that are larger than a mile
而且运行轨道可能与地球相交的天体\Nthat can intersect the Earth's orbit,
现在的目标是\Nand so the effort now is going in to
定位那些体育场大小的天体\Nfinding these sort of stadium-sized objects,
虽然不足以毁灭地球\Nthat while not completely devastating to the entire Earth,
但仍会对地球造成巨大影响\Nwould be a huge deal if they hit the Earth.
我们将小行星带留在身后\NAs we leave behind the Asteroid Belt,
驶向七大奇迹的下一站\Nwe chart a course to the next of our seven wonders,
第三奇观\Nnumber three...
火星奥林帕斯山\NOlympus Mons.
太阳系中最大的火山\Nthe largest volcano in the Solar System.
离火星越来越近\NAs we approach the planet mars,
这座硕大无朋的山体立刻吸引了我们的注意\Nwe immediately catch sight of this mammoth mountain.
山体底部直径大约350英里\NThe base of it is about almost 350 miles across,
这段距离相当于\Nthat's, as though, the base of the mountain
从洛杉矶到旧金山\Nwere from Los Angeles to San Francisco.
所以虽然海拔很高\NSo even though it's so high,
但是坡度很平缓\Nthe slope is very gradual.
你几乎无法察觉自己在爬山\NYou would barely know you were climbing a mountain.
劳拉・丹丽\N格里菲思天文台
它不是陡峭的火山\NIt's not like a steep volcano,
坡度很平缓\NIt's just... It's a smooth, low slope,
但是仿佛没有尽头\Nbut it just goes on forever.
奥林帕斯山位于塔尔西斯高地\NOlympus Mons is located in the Tharsis Bulge,
在那一地区还许多其他大型火山\Na region on the red planet that's home to other massive volcanoes.
如果你爬上13英里高的山顶\NIf you climb the 13 miles to its summit,
你可以看到火星大气的边缘\Nyou could take in a view of the very edge of the Martian atmosphere.
奥林帕斯山比地球最高峰高出许多倍\NOlympus Mons is several times higher than the highest mountains on Earth,
而山体底部更是方圆几百英里\Nand its base is hundreds of miles across.
在过去的数十亿年间\NAnd it's been formed over the last billions of years
经过一次又一次的火山喷发\Nby eruption after eruption after eruption,
由无数层的岩浆堆积而成\Nwhich has slowly surfaced it with successive layers of lava.
一亿年前  滚烫的岩浆从山顶喷涌而出\N100 million years ago, hot lava rivers poured down from its peak
覆盖了几百万平方英里的火星地表\Nto cover millions of square miles of the red planet.
坐落于夏威夷岛的莫纳罗亚山\NToday Olympus Mons is 100 times
是地球上最大的火山\Nthe volume of Earth's largest volcano, Mauna Loa,
如今的奥林帕斯山体积是它的100倍\Nlocated on the big island of Hawaii.
奥林帕斯山比地球上的一切都大许多\NOlympus Mons got so much larger than anything here,
原因有许多\Nfor, well, a number of reasons.
有一点是肯定的  那里有很多的火山运动\NOne is certainly, there was just a lot of volcanic activity.
其二则是那里的重力小很多\NA second is that mare's gravity is much lower.
你在火星上的体重会轻许多\NYou weigh a lot less on mars.
所以随着山体的增高  它不会塌方\NSo as the mountain built up, it didn't compact back down.
火山可以堆积得很高而不崩塌\NIt was able to build up to a pretty huge volcano without collapsing.
第三点\NThe third and perhaps most important reason
也许是其如此巨大最重要的原因\Nwhy Olympus Mons is so huge
火星上没有板块构造\Nis that mars doesn't have plate tectonics,
不像地球\Nthe movement of crustal plates
熔融状地幔上方的地壳会发生运动\Nthat rest on top of the molten interior of bodies, such as Earth.
奥林帕斯山体积可以增长到如此巨大\NOlympus Mons grew to such a big size
因为火星上没有板块运动\Nbecause of the lack of tectonic motions on mars.
岩浆喷涌而出的地点\NThe hot spot from which the lava, the magma, emerged
始终不变\Nremained at one location,
这就可以堆积起越来越大山体\Nallowing more and more material to build up
形成一座超级火山\Nand create a super mountain, a super volcano.
火星现在被认为处于地质不活跃期\NMars is now presumed to be geologically inactive.
但是那火山猛兽是真的已死\NBut is the volcanic beast really dead
抑或仅仅还在休眠\Nor merely a sleeping giant?
欧洲航天局的火星快车号日前捕捉到了\NThe European Space Agency's Mars Express Mission recently captured
有史以来分辨率最高的岩浆流图象\Nthe highest resolution images ever taken of the planet's lava flows.
有些可以追溯到一亿多年前\NSome flows date back 115 million years,
但还有一些仅有200万年历史\Nbut others are only 2 million years old,
以地质时间刻度来看那是很短的时间\Nand on geologic time scales that's very recent,
也就意味着现在也许还有火山喷发\Nwhich suggests there still may be some volcanic activity.
如果看看奥林帕斯山表面\NIf we look at the surface of Olympus Mons,
我们能看到有一些岩浆流之上\Nwe see especially that there are lava flows,
几乎没有陨石坑\Nwhich have very few craters on them.
于是我们知道  这些岩浆流\NAnd so, we know that those lava flows are
最老也不过一两千万年\Nperhaps 10s-20 million years old at the oldest.
但是喷发运动一直在继续\NBut the eruptive activity has been going on
如果不是一直延续到了今天\Nuntil the relatively recent past,
那也是不久之前才停止的\Nif not right up until the present day.
奥林帕斯山也许曾经产生过大量的岩浆\NOlympus Mons may have once produced vast amounts of lava,
但那地狱烈焰般的热度\Nbut its hellish heat paled in comparison
与我们太阳系七大奇观\Nto the current temperatures
榜上第二名相比\Nof number two on our countdown
则是小巫见大巫了\Nof the seven incredible wonders of our Solar System.
它远看像是个大火球\NThis may look like a ball of flames.
其表面是温度高达一万度\NBut its surface is an ocean
等离子海洋\NOf 10,000-degree plasma
伴随着大风巨浪\Nwith waves, winds
以及大规模喷发\Nand massive eruptions
堪比十亿吨TNT炸药同时爆炸\Nas explosive as a billion tons of TNT.
下一个将要探究的太阳系奇观\NOur next wonder of the Solar System
既是地球的朋友  又是最大敌人\Nhas been Earth's best friend and foe.
它用光和热笼罩着我们的星球\NIt's bathed our planet with heat and energy,
但其释放的致命高能粒子波\NBut it's also blasted us with potentially deadly
也会伤害到我们\Nhighly energetic particles and waves.
我们继续探索第二奇观\NWe now navigate around number two:
极热的太阳表面\Nthe sizzling surface of the sun.
太阳表面相当杂乱无序\NThe surface of the sun is really quite chaotic.
它持续沸腾  不断冒泡\NIt's always boiling and bubbling.
还从太阳内部\NIn particular, there are hot cells of gas
释放出热能气体\Nthat come out from the interior up,
散发能量  逐渐冷却\Nradiate their energy, cool,
然后下沉回去\Nand then, come back down.
这种对流过程\NSo this convection, as it's called,
艾力克斯・菲利潘科\N加州大学  伯克利分校
这种沸腾运动\NThis boiling motion, similar to
与水的沸腾非常相似\Nwhat you see in a boiling pot of water,
是在地表附近发生的\Nis occurring near the surface.
时至今日\NWe have never been able to
我们终于可以\Nlook at the sun's surface
直视太阳表面\Nup close until now.
此部分字幕有误,以后补加。
克利福德・约翰逊\N南加州大学
人造卫星最新采集行动
即拍摄我们守护之星的图像
这些稀有影像让人感觉\NThese unprecedented movies make you feel like
太阳光球层表面\Nyou're an arm's distance away
已经触手可及\Nfrom touching the sun's visible surface called the Photosphere.
太阳风暴及其他剧烈活动\NThis is where solar storms
就发生在这一层\Nand other violent phenomena occur.
如果你能完好无损的到达太阳表面\NThe surface of the sun,
你会发现那里\Nif you were somehow able to go there and protect yourself,
非常嘈杂  异常炎热  活动的非常猛烈\Nis an incredibly noisy, hot and violent place.
表层温度高达数千度\NThere are temperatures thousands of degrees.
格瑞格・拉夫林\N加州大学  圣克鲁兹分校
还有持续不断的磁暴\NThere are continuous magnetic storms
并伴随雷鸣般的声响\Nthat create huge, basically thunder-like sounds.
在最新纪录影像中 \NIn this new movie,
美国太阳动力学观测卫星\NNASA's Solar Dynamics Observatory
记录了一次日珥爆发\Nrecorded a Prominence.
这是一簇相对低温的等离子\NThis is a relatively cool, dense cloud of plasma
受磁力影响\Nthat sits suspended above the solar surface,
悬浮于太阳表面\Nsupported by magnec forces.
如图所示\NAs seen here, Prominences
艾米・梅泽\N美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
引起等离子大爆炸\NAnd these throw up giant blasts of plasma
形成的日珥有着奇怪的弧度\NThat come out along curious looking arcs.
但这些日珥仍循\NBut these are actually following
太阳磁力线的轨迹\Nthe magnetic field lines around the sun.
爆发出的日珥也会\NEruptive Prominences can occur in tandem
与另一个日珥相互串联\Nwith another solar ejection.
而对地球的破坏力\NThat can deliver a double punch,
也将加倍\Nif directed at the Earth.
美国太阳和太阳风层探测器\NNASA's Solar and Heliospheric Observatory
即SOHO\Nor SOHO,
近日拍摄到一组\Nrecently took dramatic movies
大规模日冕物质抛射\Nof Coronal Mass Ejections,
即CMEs\Nor CMEs.
这些高温电离气体组成的气泡\NThese massive bubbles of hot ionized gas
含有高达一百亿吨的太阳物质\Ncontain up to 10 billion tons of solar material.
它们以几百万英里的时速\NThey shoot out into space
喷向太空\Nat speeds of several million miles an hour.
日冕物质抛射属于超大型太阳风\NCoronal Mass Ejections are incredibly powerful storms.
劳拉・丹丽\N格里菲思天文台
光是那巨大的能量\NThey can be as massive as a billion h-bombs,
就比得上十亿颗氢弹\Njust huge amounts of energy.
那些等离子射到地球时\NAnd sometimes those big blobs of plasma strike the Earth
会形成美丽的北极光\Nand lead to beautiful northern lights, aurorae displays.
也会对地球造成相当大的损害\NThey can also be very harmful to the Earth.
当日冕物质抛射产物射向地球时\NWhen large Coronal Mass Ejections are blasted toward Earth
会触发磁暴\Nthey can trigger geomagnetic storms.
这些电离粒子\NThese blobs of ionized particles
会损害甚至摧毁卫星\Ncan damage or even terminate satellites
更会破坏地球上的电网\Nas well as fry our electrical grids.
更有甚者\NWhat's more,
进行太空行走时\NThey're extremely hazardous to astronauts
这些粒子会对宇航员造成极大的伤害\Nwhen outside of the protection of a spacecraft.
日冕物质抛射会释放X射线\NThe CMEs generate X-Rays.
因此进行太空行走时\NSo, if you're out in space,
如果遇到日冕物质抛射\Nyou would get quite a dose of radiation,
会被严重辐射到\Nif you were in one of these CMEs.
幸运的是大气层吸收了绝大部分射线\NLuckily, our atmosphere absorbs most of the X-Rays,
因此在地表\Nand we don't experience the bad effects here
不会受到影响\Non the surface of the Earth.
这些最新拍摄的影像令人心生畏惧\NThese latest images are chilling reminders
提醒我们必须时刻关注太阳表面活动\Nthat our sun's surface is a force to reckon with.
在不久的将来\NAnd things may really heat up on our home star
太阳表面也许会持续升温\Nin the very near future.
太阳活动以十一年为一个周期\NSolar activity runs through an 11-year cycle.
2013年将达到顶峰\NIn 2013, our sun will be at the peak of this cycle
因此也称为太阳峰年\Ncalled the Solar Maximum.
此时\NAt this time,
太阳表面会爆发超级风暴\Nthe surface of the sun could create the perfect storm.
太阳曾经爆发过太阳风\NThe sun has had in the past big solar storms
破坏了地球上的电网\Nthat have knocked out power grids
并中断通讯卫星\Nand our communication satellites.
将来也会爆发更多太阳风\NThere will be more storms.
在我们这一代  甚至接下来的几千年里\NThey might happen at any time or they may not happen,
随时都可能爆发  也可能再也不爆发\Nyou know, in our lifetime or even in the next millennium.
我们只是不知道\NWe just don't know.
但太阳风暴无法破坏\NBut one thing a solar storm can't destroy
太阳系七大奇观中的\Nis number one on our countdown of the seven wonders
第一奇观\Nof our Solar System,
它是太阳系第五大行星\NIt's the fifth largest planet.
其十分之一的表面\NOne tenth of its surface
终年覆盖冰雪\Nis permanently covered with ice,
它的内部炽热无比  蕴藏着大量岩浆\NAnd its hot interior has been churning up enough magma
地表的火山因而持续喷发数十亿年\Nto keep volcanoes erupting for billions of years.
太阳系七大奇观探索之旅\NThe exploration of our cosmic neighborhood
将以第一大奇观压轴\Nclimaxes with a touchdown on number one of the seven wonders,
那就是地球\NEarth
毫无疑问\NThe Earth, without a doubt,
地球是太阳系独一无二的伟大奇迹\Nis the single greatest wonder in the Solar System.
艾力克斯・菲利潘科\N加州大学  伯克利分校
非常适合人类的生存\NThe Earth is so perfect for our existence.
有液态水\NThere's liquid water.
有大气层\NThere's an atmosphere.
有舒适的温度\NThere's comfortable temperatures.
这是个极好的星球\NIt's just a great place.
地球是距离太阳第三远的行星 \NEarth, the third planet from the sun,
其魅力令人窒息\Nis brimming with breathtaking beauty.
跟太阳系其他天体不同\NUnlike any other body in the Solar System,
地球有将近2/3的表面被水覆盖\Nliquid water covers nearly 2/3 of its surface.
各大洲陆地景观各不相同\NIts continents inherited a diverse landscape,
它拥有全宇宙\Nand it's the only planet confirmed
最独特的生态环境\Nto support life in all its amazing forms.
地球许多独有特征\NEarth has a number of different features
使其在太阳系中变得独一无二\Nthat make it truly unique in our Solar System.
比如说\NFor one thing,
地球既不会出现铄石流金的高温\Nit's not boiling hot
艾米・梅泽\N美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
也不会出现冰天雪地的低温\Nand nor is it freezing cold.
地球与太阳的距离适中\NIt's just at the right distance from the sun
使地球温度适宜  有利于生命体的发展\Nto be a very moderate temperature that supports life.
再比如说\NFor another thing,
地球既不完全被水所覆盖\Nit's not completely a water world
也不完全被干燥的沙漠所覆盖\Nnor is it completely a dry desert either.
水陆配合相得益彰\NIt's got just the right mix of land and ocean
进而支持多种生物的发展\Nto support a wide variety of species.
科学通过研究\NScience is now getting closer
地球的形成过程\Nto solving the mystery of how life got started
逐渐揭开了生命起源的神秘面纱\Nby retracing the steps of our planet's formation.
46亿年前\N4.6 billion years ago,
太阳形成的过程中\NIn the swirling disk of debris
遗留了许多相互绕转的碎片\Nleft over from the formation of our newborn sun,
气体和尘埃粒子\Ngas and dust particles
开始聚集在一起\Nbegan to clump together.
最终形成巨大的岩石和冰川\NThey eventually formed large boulders made of rock and ice
就如今天的小行星和彗星\Nthat we see today as asteroids and comets.
几百万年前\NFor millions of years,
这些天体相撞\Nthese bodies collided
然后又组合形成行星\Nand coalesced to form planets.
地球需要一些特殊物质\NDuring this birthing process,
才能完成这样的形成过程\NEarth acquired some special properties.
地球独有的特征\NOne unique feature on Earth
就是有丰富的水资源\Nis abundant liquid water.
被认为是早期火山爆发时形成的\NIt is thought that the earliest volcanoes
大量水蒸气\Nspewed out massive amounts of steam,
凝结成雨\Nwhich condensed into rain
从而滋润了整个星球\Nand supplied the planet with water.
但最近对于水的来源又有了新的说法\NBut recently, new sources of water have been suggested.
有些水源\NSome of that water
可能是来自彗星\Nmight have come from comets
有些水源可能是来自\Nor some of the water might have come
小行星带外围\Nfrom an outer Belt of Asteroids
那里富含水汽\Nthat was rich in water.
换句话说  有些水源\NIn other words, some of the water
甚至可能来自陨石\Ncould have come from the rocks
就是宇宙大爆炸后\Nthat made the Earth near the end
形成地球的陨石\Nof this Era of Heavy Bombardment.
水源的出现是生命起源的关键\NAnd water appears to be a key component for the origin of life.
理论认为\NIt was previously theorized
生命起源于原始水洼中\Nthat life began in a primordial soup,
温暖的水汽中含有大量能源和大气成分\Na warm pond containing energy and atmospheric elements
从而形成氨基酸\Nto make Amino Acids.
然而  最近的开创性研究宣称\NHowever, the most recent pioneering research makes a strong claim
地球自身拥有的化学能源\Nthat the Earth's own chemical energy
及丰富蛋白质\Nand rich proteins seeped up
通过大洋深处的喷口渗透出来\Nthrough hydrothermal vents deep under the ocean.
随着时间的推移  这些混合物\NOver time, this mixture
产生了细胞生命\Njump-started life
从而加速了生命的形成\Nby producing living cells.
众所周知  \NWe know that liquid water
劳拉・丹丽\N格里菲思天文台
水是生命之源\Nis essential to life,
生命可能产生于水中\Nand life probably got started in a water environment,
究竟是产生于大洋深处的火山喷发\Nwhether it's in the deep ocean at the volcanic vents
还是浅洼中\Nor in a shallow pond,
我们无法得知\NWe don't really know
生命是从哪里起源  是怎样形成的\Nwhere and how precisely life got started here.
但是地球产生了生命\NBut it did.
地球是唯一我们所知\NAnd it's the only planet that we know
存在生命的星球\Nwhere life actually exists.
不论生命是怎样形成的\NRegardless of how life started,
一次巧合\Na fortunate event
使得生命向复杂进化成为可能\Nmade it possible for complex creatures to evolve.
大约30亿年前\NAbout 3 billion years ago,
原始的地下水细菌为了生存\Nancient underwater bacteria
开始利用水  二氧化碳  太阳能\Nbegan to use water, Carbon Dioxide and the sun's energy
化合生成碳水化合物\Nto produce Carbohydrates in order to survive.
这个过程  被称作光合作用\NThis process, called Photosynthesis,
光合作用形成的氧气溶解进海水中\Ninjected vast amounts of oxygen into seawater,
并逐渐形成今日的大气层\Nand eventually, our atmosphere.
生命不断进化\NA huge step happened in evolution
地球也逐渐被氧气包围\Nwhen the Earth got polluted with oxygen.
地球形成伊始大气中并没有充足的氧气\NWe didn't start with a rich oxygen atmosphere!
但是后来  \NBut later,
光合作用不断产生氧气\Nthe oxygen atmosphere that developed on Earth, basically from Photosynthesis,
促使生命体愈加复杂\Nallowed life to get a lot more complex.
地球数十亿年间持续发展\NAfter a few billion years of planetary
生物也不断进化\Nand biological evolution,
动植物也渐渐向陆地发展\Nthe first plants and animals emerged from water on to land.
据估计\NIt's estimated
现代人类历史\Nthat modern humans came onto the scene
仅仅20多万年\Na mere 200,000 years ago,
人类的进化也伴随着技术革命\Nand with our evolution came the technological revolution of the planet.
从古代人建造的遗迹\NFrom ancient man-made monuments
到如今繁华的都市\Nto bustling metropolitan cities,
人类开始从空间和地域上\NHuman Beings changed the way
改变地球的面貌\NEarth looks on the ground and from space.
地球的面貌\NThe Earth's surface has started to be modified
受到人类城市建设的影响\Nvery significantly by cities,
发生了翻天覆地的变化\Nby human activity.
人类只是地球的一部分\NWe're part of the Earth.
我们改变了地球的原本样貌\NWe've created all these changes on its surface.
从深层意义来说\NAnd so, the Earth's geology,
地球的地质情况\Nin some deep sense,
因为城市的出现\Nhas been radically altered
格瑞格・拉夫林\N加州大学  圣克鲁兹分校
因为人类在地球上修建的大小建筑\Nby the appearances of cities,
已经被彻底改变\Nby the appearances of all the things that we do on the surface,
这尤其需要注意\Nand that's something that's remarkable,
据我们所知\Nand which, as far as we know,
别的星球还没有过这种变化\Nis not happening anywhere else.
太阳系其他星球上更没有过\NCertainly, it's not happening anywhere else in our own Solar System.
我们已经探索了\NOur cosmic tour has taken us
七大奇观\Nto seven wondrous sights,
土卫二间歇性冰泉\Nthe Icy Geyser-Laden Moon, Enceladus,
土星美丽的光环 \NSaturn's sensational rings,
木星大红斑 \NJupiter's Great Red Spot,
最大的火山  火星奥林帕斯山\Nthe largest volcano, Olympus Mons,
神秘的小行星带\Nthe mysterious Asteroid Belt
以及炙热的太阳\NAnd our stormy sun.
这些难忘的冒险中\NBut this unforgettable adventure
可不能缺了我们家园地球的身影\Nwould not have been possible without our home planet, Earth,
这里一切皆有可能\NA place with endless possibilities.
上个世纪\NOver the last century,
人类已经冶炼出金属以及其他材料\Nhumans have manufactured metals and other materials
用于建造宇宙飞船\Nfrom our planet's crust to build spacecraft.
先进技术使得我们 \NOur technology will enable us to blast off
可以探索太空奇观\Nto explore the other wonders.
我们惊叹于这些遥远的奇观\NWe'll be able to marvel at these distant domains,
更意识到自己是广袤宇宙一部分\Nand realize that we're part of a much wider cosmic world.
巍巍奇观  发人深省\NThese awe-inspiring phenomena allow us to ponder
我们究竟是谁  又从何而来\Nwho are we and why we are here.
这片壮丽天地\NIn this magnificent place,
便是宇宙\Nwe call the Universe.