[Script Info]
; Script generated by Aegisub 2.1.8
; http://www.aegisub.org/
Title:夏末秋字幕组
Original Script:Red Bee Media Ltd.
Synch Point:0
ScriptType: v4.00+
Collisions:Normal
Timer:100.0000

[V4+ Styles]
Format: Name, Fontname, Fontsize, PrimaryColour, SecondaryColour, OutlineColour, BackColour, Bold, Italic, Underline, StrikeOut, ScaleX, ScaleY, Spacing, Angle, BorderStyle, Outline, Shadow, Alignment, MarginL, MarginR, MarginV, Encoding
Style: Default,方正兰亭中黑_GBK,18,&HFFFFFF,&H000000,&H40000000,&H70000000,-1,0,0,0,100,100,0,0.00,1,1,1,2,5,5,5,134

[Events]
Format: Layer, Start, End, Style, Name, MarginL, MarginR, MarginV, Effect, Text
Dialogue: 0,0:00:11.28,0:00:14.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们为什么存在？ 我们来自哪里？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Why are we here? Where do we come from?
Dialogue: 0,0:00:14.68,0:00:17.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是人类一直在问的问题\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These are the most enduring of questions.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:17.92,0:00:22.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,追根问底 寻找答案 这是人类的本性\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it's an essential part of human nature to want to find the answers.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:28.80,0:00:34.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,人类的起源可以追溯到千万年前\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And we can trace that ancestry back hundreds of thousands of years to the dawn of humankind.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:34.52,0:00:39.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但事实上 我们的故事还要早得多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But in reality, our story extends far further back in time.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:39.64,0:00:43.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从宇宙诞生之日起 就已经揭开了序幕\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our story starts with the beginning of the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:47.28,0:00:51.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一切开始于137亿年前\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It began 13.7 billion years ago.
Dialogue: 0,0:00:56.08,0:00:59.73,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如今 宇宙中有数千亿个星系\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And today it's filled with over 100 billion galaxies,
Dialogue: 0,0:00:59.73,0:01:03.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,每个星系又包含数千亿颗恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}each containing hundreds of billions of stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:09.52,0:01:13.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这档节目中 我要向您讲述宇宙的故事\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In the series, I want to tell that story
Dialogue: 0,0:01:13.04,0:01:16.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为归根到底 我们都是宇宙的一部分\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because ultimately we are part of the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:16.20,0:01:19.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所以 宇宙的故事就是我们的故事\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So its story is our story.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:24.96,0:01:26.47,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,有一个东西非常重要 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's a story that you couldn't tell
Dialogue: 0,0:01:26.47,0:01:28.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,没有它 宇宙的故事就无从讲起\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}without something so fundamental
Dialogue: 0,0:01:28.60,0:01:31.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,没有它 就无法想象宇宙会变成什么样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that it's impossible to imagine the universe without it.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:31.76,0:01:36.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它存在于宇宙的每一个角落 那就是时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's woven into the very fabric of the cosmos. Time.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:41.28,0:01:46.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间的流逝造就了宇宙的演变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The relentless flow of time has driven the evolution of the universe
Dialogue: 0,0:01:46.08,0:01:49.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也诞生了许多非凡的奇迹\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and created many extraordinary wonders.
Dialogue: 0,0:01:52.68,0:01:56.22,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些奇迹见证了宇宙的初生 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These wonders take us from the very first moments
Dialogue: 0,0:01:56.22,0:01:58.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也将伴随它走向灭亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in the life of the universe to its eventual end.
Dialogue: 0,0:02:00.00,0:02:12.70,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\fe134\fad(500,1000)\c&HFFFFFF&\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\bord0.5}本字幕由{\fs19\fn方正黑体简体\c&H26F4FF&} 花之翼 s星形嵌段 merlin 姚敏Neutrino 桃夭 statm {\fe134\fn方正准圆简体\c&HFFFFFF&\fs16}翻译制作\N{\fn方正准圆简体\fscy100\fe134\fn方正准圆简体\c&HFFFFFF&\fs16}校对/后期制作 {\fs18\fn方正黑体简体\c&H26F4FF&}statm{\c&H0080ff&\fn方正黑体简体\fs18}【夏末秋字幕组】
Dialogue: 0,0:02:13.50,0:02:19.30,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\fe134\fad(1000,1000)\pos(190,277)\fs17\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}我们立志翻译各种人文科学纪录片\N需要您的知识 充实自己 服务大众\N加入我们 联系QQ:245801957【长期招募】\N--==学术 交流 奉献==--
Dialogue: 0,0:02:13.50,0:02:19.30,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\fad(1000,1000)\fs16\c&HFFFFFF&\pos(196,122)\shad1\3c&H9B9B9B&\fn方正兰亭准黑_GBK\4c&H474747&}第一集   天地宿命
Dialogue: 0,0:02:29.08,0:02:32.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里是秘鲁西北海岸线上的Chankillo\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is Chankillo on the north-western coast of Peru.
Dialogue: 0,0:02:32.04,0:02:37.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一个鲜为人知的南美洲考古遗址\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it's one of South America's lesser known archaeological sites.
Dialogue: 0,0:02:37.48,0:02:40.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我却觉得 这片地方无比引人入胜\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But, for me, it is surely one of the most fascinating.
Dialogue: 0,0:02:49.60,0:02:54.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,大约2500年前 存在着一个我们所知甚少的文明\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Around 2,500 years ago, a civilisation we know almost nothing about
Dialogue: 0,0:02:54.68,0:02:57.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,他们在沙漠中建造了这座坚固的庙宇\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}built this fortified temple in the desert.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:02.96,0:03:07.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,庙宇的围墙曾经是亮白色的 上面画着人物\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Its walls were once brilliant white and covered with painted figures.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:11.48,0:03:14.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如今 几乎所有的装饰\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Today, all but the smallest fragments
Dialogue: 0,0:03:14.00,0:03:15.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都早已随风飘散\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of the decorations are gone.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:15.68,0:03:21.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一切文化和语言的蛛丝马迹也已经遗失\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The details of this culture and all traces of its language are lost.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:26.32,0:03:29.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 如果你站在正确的位置上 依然能体会到\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And yet, if you stand in the right place, you can still experience
Dialogue: 0,0:03:29.88,0:03:32.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,Chankillo的真正意义 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the true purpose of Chankillo,
Dialogue: 0,0:03:32.84,0:03:36.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,理解古人在修建它时 想要传达的讯息\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in just the same way as you could the day that it was built.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:40.68,0:03:43.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,不过要想揭开Chankillo的奥秘 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But, to do that, you have to be here
Dialogue: 0,0:03:43.08,0:03:44.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,你得在日出之前来到这里\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}before the sun rises.
Dialogue: 0,0:03:59.16,0:04:02.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些古塔组成了一个太阳历\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These towers form an ancient solar calendar.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:02.68,0:04:05.35,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着一年里日期的改变 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now, at different times of year,
Dialogue: 0,0:04:05.35,0:04:09.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,日出点在地平线上的位置也有所不同\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the sunrise point is at a different place on the horizon.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:09.24,0:04:12.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,12月21日 在南半球这里\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}21st December, which here in the southern hemisphere
Dialogue: 0,0:04:12.44,0:04:15.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是夏至 也就是一年中日照时间最长的一天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is the summer solstice, the longest day,
Dialogue: 0,0:04:15.80,0:04:20.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而太阳正好会移动到最右边的塔上 从那里升起\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the sun rises just to the right of the right-most tower.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:20.32,0:04:25.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着时间流逝 日出点会沿着这些塔移动 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Then, as the year passes, the sun moves through the towers
Dialogue: 0,0:04:25.40,0:04:29.85,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,直到6月21日 冬至 日照时间最短的一天 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}until on 21st June, the winter solstice, the shortest day,
Dialogue: 0,0:04:29.85,0:04:33.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳会移动到最左边的塔上 从那儿升起\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it rises just to left of the left-most tower.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:33.04,0:04:38.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,实际上就在远处的山和最左边那座塔之间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Actually just in between that mountain you can see in the distance and the left-most tower.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:38.76,0:04:42.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一年中的任何时间 只要你观察日出\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So, at any time of year, if you watch the sun rise,
Dialogue: 0,0:04:42.24,0:04:45.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就可以根据日出点 得知大概的日期\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}you can measure its position and you can tell,
Dialogue: 0,0:04:45.76,0:04:49.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,误差很小 只有两三天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}within an accuracy of two or three days, the date.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:49.56,0:04:53.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,今天是9月15日\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Today's date is September the 15th.
Dialogue: 0,0:04:53.08,0:04:58.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是说 太阳会在第五和第六座塔之间升起\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So that means the sun will rise between the fifth and the sixth towers.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:10.24,0:05:14.15,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,Chankillo的日历依然准确 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Chankillo still works as a calendar
Dialogue: 0,0:05:14.15,0:05:16.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为从那时到现在\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because the sun still rises in the same place today
Dialogue: 0,0:05:16.00,0:05:19.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳一直从相同的地方升起\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as it did when these stones were first laid down.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:24.24,0:05:29.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,红彤彤的太阳从塔上蓬勃而出 多么壮观啊\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That's a magnificent sight, as the sun burns through the towers.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:36.96,0:05:41.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这里 你能触摸到过去 想象一下它以前的样子\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You can almost feel the presence of the past here. Imagine what it must have been like.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:41.08,0:05:45.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,成千上万的居民站在这里迎接太阳\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Thousands of citizens stood here to greet the sun,
Dialogue: 0,0:05:45.36,0:05:48.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳是神的存在 是他们的上帝\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}which was almost certainly a deity. Almost certainly their god.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:48.76,0:05:51.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是多么伟大的成就\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}What a magnificent achievement.
Dialogue: 0,0:05:51.52,0:05:54.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它可能是人类对于星球运行规律\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Probably one of our earliest attempts
Dialogue: 0,0:05:54.56,0:05:57.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最早的探索之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to begin to measure the heavens.
Dialogue: 0,0:06:10.64,0:06:12.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,历经千年之后\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Over the millennia,
Dialogue: 0,0:06:12.28,0:06:16.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这种对茫茫宇宙的探索欲望\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that desire to measure what's going on in the sky
Dialogue: 0,0:06:16.80,0:06:19.89,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,启迪我们开创了现代天文学 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}has led to modern astronomy
Dialogue: 0,0:06:19.89,0:06:22.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,为现代文明打下了基石\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the foundations of our modern civilisation.
Dialogue: 0,0:06:31.68,0:06:33.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我也要在花园里建一排这样的塔\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I might build one in my garden.
Dialogue: 0,0:06:37.40,0:06:39.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,多有趣啊！\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I want one!
Dialogue: 0,0:06:48.56,0:06:52.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这十三座连成一排的塔 体现了人类\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The 13 towers that line this ridge stand testament to our
Dialogue: 0,0:06:52.52,0:06:57.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,对天体运行规律的持续不断的兴趣\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}enduring fascination with the clockwork of the heavens.
Dialogue: 0,0:06:57.40,0:07:03.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也印证了人类和宇宙的深邃联系\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And to the direct connection between our lives and the cosmos.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:04.64,0:07:08.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,日升 日落 犹如心跳一般\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The rising and setting of the sun provides an epic heartbeat
Dialogue: 0,0:07:08.16,0:07:11.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,告诉我们时间在流逝\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that allows us to mark the passage of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:19.84,0:07:25.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一天有24小时 这是地球自转一周的时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}A day on Earth is the 24 hours it takes our planet to rotate once on its axis.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:34.16,0:07:37.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一个月有29.5天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our months are based on the 29-and-a-half days
Dialogue: 0,0:07:37.68,0:07:41.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是月亮在夜空中呈现出阴晴圆缺的周期\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it takes the moon to wax and wane in the night sky.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:44.80,0:07:48.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一年有365.25天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And a year is the 365-and-a-quarter days
Dialogue: 0,0:07:48.36,0:07:52.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是地球绕太阳一周的时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it takes us to orbit once around the sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:54.64,0:07:59.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些我们熟悉的时间尺度 标志了我们生命的节奏\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These familiar timescales mark the passing of our lives.
Dialogue: 0,0:07:59.60,0:08:04.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,相比较而言 宇宙的生命却长得多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But the life of the universe plays out on a much grander scale.
Dialogue: 0,0:08:08.76,0:08:12.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当我们仰望星空时 看到的不只是恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}When you look up into the night sky, you don't just see stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:08:12.96,0:08:17.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所有的星星点点 就像无数个不同的时钟\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Those tiny points of light are a million different clocks,
Dialogue: 0,0:08:17.84,0:08:23.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些恒星见证了数十亿 甚至数万亿年的流逝\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}whose lifespans mark out the passage of time over billions, or even trillions, of years.
Dialogue: 0,0:08:32.88,0:08:36.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这部影片向您讲述时间的广度\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This film is about the greatest expanses of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:08:36.68,0:08:40.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间无处不在 它雕琢了我们的宇宙\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The deep time that shapes the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:08:42.52,0:08:48.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从欲火而生 到无数代的恒星 行星和星系\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}From its fiery beginnings, through countless generations of stars, planets and galaxies,
Dialogue: 0,0:08:48.60,0:08:50.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,直到最终的消亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to its eventual demise,
Dialogue: 0,0:08:50.52,0:08:55.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙的命运 由时间之手全然掌控\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the fate of the universe is determined by the passage of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:09:04.48,0:09:07.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙里的时间尺度非常大 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Timescales in the cosmos seem so unimaginably vast,
Dialogue: 0,0:09:07.36,0:09:10.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,几乎没有任何东西能与之相提并论\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it's almost impossible to relate to them.
Dialogue: 0,0:09:12.48,0:09:15.99,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 在地球上的某些地方 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Yet there are places on Earth
Dialogue: 0,0:09:15.99,0:09:18.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,能让我们对此有一些认识\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}where we can begin to encounter time on these universal scales.
Dialogue: 0,0:09:26.64,0:09:29.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里是位于哥斯达黎加北部 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is Ostional
Dialogue: 0,0:09:29.20,0:09:32.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太平洋海岸上的Ostional\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}on the northern Pacific coast of Costa Rica.
Dialogue: 0,0:09:32.16,0:09:37.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我来这里观察一个自然现象\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And I've come here to witness a natural event that's been happening
Dialogue: 0,0:09:37.08,0:09:40.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这个现象在人类诞生之前就已存在了无数年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}long before there were any humans here to see it.
Dialogue: 0,0:09:40.76,0:09:46.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我认为 这是一扇观察远古地球的窗口\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And I suppose it really is a window into the distant past of life on our planet.
Dialogue: 0,0:10:09.76,0:10:16.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,每当日落西山 月亮升起 海潮到来之时\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Once the sun has dipped below the horizon and the moon conspired to make the tides just right,
Dialogue: 0,0:10:16.00,0:10:20.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就会有一些史前生物造访这个沙滩\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}this beach is visited by prehistoric creatures.
Dialogue: 0,0:10:31.44,0:10:34.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在夜幕的掩护下 它们从海水中涌上来\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Under the cover of darkness, they emerge from the ocean.
Dialogue: 0,0:10:43.16,0:10:46.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,Playa Ostional是世界上为数不多的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Playa Ostional is one of the few beaches in the world
Dialogue: 0,0:10:46.24,0:10:49.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,海龟筑巢地之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}where large numbers of sea turtles make their nests.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:00.44,0:11:04.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最另人称道的是 这幅景象已经在这里\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But what makes this truly remarkable is the sheer length of time
Dialogue: 0,0:11:04.52,0:11:07.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,上演了亿万年的岁月\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}scenes like this have been playing out.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:13.36,0:11:17.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是地球上最古老的生物之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is part of one of the oldest life-cycles on Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:17.24,0:11:22.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在过去一亿年里 每到这样的夜晚 海龟们\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}On nights like these, for the last 100 million years, turtles like this
Dialogue: 0,0:11:22.76,0:11:27.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都会在这里上岸产蛋\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}have been hauling themselves out of the ocean to lay their eggs.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:29.56,0:11:32.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这么长的时间 太不可思议了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's an almost incomprehensible timespan.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:32.76,0:11:36.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一亿年前 恐龙还在地球上四处游荡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}100 million years ago, there were dinosaurs roaming the Earth,
Dialogue: 0,0:11:36.96,0:11:39.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,不过那时的地球和现在有很大不同\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}but the Earth itself looked very different.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:39.96,0:11:43.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,南美洲和北美洲并不相连\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}South America was not connected to North America.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:43.84,0:11:47.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,北美洲在欧洲附近\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}North America was somewhere over close to Europe.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:47.36,0:11:50.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而澳洲和南极接壤\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Australia was connected to Antarctica.
Dialogue: 0,0:11:57.00,0:11:59.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这真是...\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It really is quite...
Dialogue: 0,0:11:59.04,0:12:04.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,能和这种远古生物近距离接触 真是太不可思议了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}wonderful to be so close to such an ancient cycle of life.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:05.64,0:12:08.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我能听到他的呼吸声\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I can hear breathing, actually.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:20.88,0:12:23.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这种经历太神奇了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So, a remarkable experience.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:23.12,0:12:26.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这样一个平凡的夜晚\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I mean, it really is beautiful to see that.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:26.52,0:12:32.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们看到了数亿年前的生物 这种感觉实在太美妙了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}On one night of many hundreds of millions of nights stretching back into the past.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:41.84,0:12:43.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,她走了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And she's gone.
Dialogue: 0,0:12:53.92,0:12:59.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这一刻 远古时代大门仿佛向我们洞开\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}To witness a moment like this is to open up a connection to the deep past.
Dialogue: 0,0:13:02.52,0:13:07.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,让我们见识到人类诞生之前的远古时代\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}To experience timespans far longer than the history of our own species.
Dialogue: 0,0:13:09.12,0:13:13.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而即使是这些海龟上亿年的故事\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Yet even the 100-million-year story of the turtles
Dialogue: 0,0:13:13.96,0:13:18.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,和宇宙近乎无限的时间跨度相比 只是短短一瞬\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}only begins to connect us with the vast sweep of cosmic time.
Dialogue: 0,0:13:25.20,0:13:28.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们整个太阳系 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our entire solar system is travelling
Dialogue: 0,0:13:28.04,0:13:30.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,正绕着银河系的中心\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}on an unimaginably vast orbit,
Dialogue: 0,0:13:30.76,0:13:33.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在一个极其广阔的轨道上旋转\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}spinning around the centre of our galaxy.
Dialogue: 0,0:13:40.76,0:13:46.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而围绕银河系转一圈 就要花上两亿五千万年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It takes 250 million years to make just one circuit of the Milky Way.
Dialogue: 0,0:13:53.80,0:13:56.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在整个人类史中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In the entire history of the human race,
Dialogue: 0,0:13:56.52,0:14:01.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳系走过的路程 还不到这轨道的1%\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we've travelled less than a tenth of 1% of that orbit.
Dialogue: 0,0:14:05.68,0:14:10.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些周期看上去 是永恒不变的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These cycles seem eternal and unchanging,
Dialogue: 0,0:14:10.08,0:14:15.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但当时间的故事慢慢展开 一条真理也随之被揭示\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}but as the story of time unfolds, a fundamental truth is revealed.
Dialogue: 0,0:14:20.52,0:14:22.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,万物都不能长久\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Nothing lasts forever.
Dialogue: 0,0:14:29.96,0:14:32.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是时间最深刻的特质\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is the most profound property of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:14:37.16,0:14:39.41,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在广袤的宇宙中是如此 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it plays out just as vividly here on Earth
Dialogue: 0,0:14:39.41,0:14:43.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而在地球上 我们也能找到同样鲜活的例证\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as it does in the depths of space.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:01.84,0:15:06.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是阿根廷南部巴塔哥尼亚地区的莫雷诺冰川\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Well, this is the Perito Moreno Glacier in Patagonia in southern Argentina.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:06.68,0:15:10.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是上百条从巴塔哥尼亚南部冰原地区\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it's one of the hundreds of glaciers
Dialogue: 0,0:15:10.64,0:15:14.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,延伸下来的冰川之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that sweep down the continent from the southern Patagonian ice fields.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:16.64,0:15:21.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如果你朝着这个方向再往南走一千公里\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And, you know, if you carry on that way, south about 1,000 kilometres,
Dialogue: 0,0:15:21.76,0:15:24.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,你就到达了南美洲的最南边\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}you get to the end of South America.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:24.40,0:15:27.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,自此之后 一直到南极之间 只有茫茫大海\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}From then on, there's nothing to the Antarctic.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:27.72,0:15:30.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,...这儿还真有南极的感觉\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it feels like that today.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:41.08,0:15:45.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些延展如此宽广的冰川 第一眼看上去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The glacier is such a massive expanse of ice that, at first sight,
Dialogue: 0,0:15:45.76,0:15:50.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就像宇宙中的周期一样 是静止的 一成不变的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}just like the cycles of the heavens, it appears fixed and unchanging.
Dialogue: 0,0:15:59.92,0:16:03.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但若细细观察 就会发现 冰川正在不停地移动着\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Yet, seen close-up, it's continually on the move.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:03.76,0:16:07.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,千万年来一直如此\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As it has been for tens of thousands of years.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:23.88,0:16:28.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,整个冰川的边缘向湖中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The whole face of the glacier is moving into the lake
Dialogue: 0,0:16:28.64,0:16:31.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,每天移动大概这么长\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}something like that much every day.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:31.88,0:16:36.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这意味着每年有两亿五千万吨的冰\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That means that well over a quarter of a billion tonnes of ice
Dialogue: 0,0:16:36.32,0:16:40.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从冰川上坠落到湖里\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}drop off the face of the glacier into the lake every year.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:40.28,0:16:41.71,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,算下来大约是每天10万吨 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That's about a million tonnes a day.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:41.71,0:16:43.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,并且你可以通过声音感受到它的运动\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And you can hear it happening.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:43.48,0:16:48.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时不时的 你就会听到那种巨大的破碎声\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Just every now and again, you hear this tremendous cracking sound.
Dialogue: 0,0:16:48.04,0:16:50.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就好像这地方是活着的一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It really is like the place is alive.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:03.76,0:17:06.62,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当这些庞大的冰块坠落到湖里时 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You know, it's quite disturbing
Dialogue: 0,0:17:06.63,0:17:08.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,让人感到有些害怕\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}when these enormous chunks of ice fall into the lake.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:08.16,0:17:12.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然冰川看上去平静 而且运动速度极度缓慢\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Although this thing seems stable and the movement seems glacially slow,
Dialogue: 0,0:17:12.88,0:17:17.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也会有很猛烈的崩塌\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}actually there can be really violent collapses.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:17.64,0:17:21.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是一个极度活跃的地方\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's an incredibly dynamic place to be.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:32.88,0:17:38.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,冰川的运动从一个侧面让我们体察到时间的本质\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The movements of the glacier provide an insight into the nature of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:38.24,0:17:41.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这就是事物发生的顺序性\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It is simply the ordering of events into sequences.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:41.80,0:17:44.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一步接着一步\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}One step after another.
Dialogue: 0,0:17:48.72,0:17:53.45,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着时间推移 雪花飘落 冰川形成 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As time passes, snow falls, ice forms,
Dialogue: 0,0:17:53.45,0:17:56.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一寸寸地向山谷下前进\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the glacier gradually inches down the valley
Dialogue: 0,0:17:56.24,0:17:59.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最后大片的冰块崩塌入湖\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and huge chunks of ice fall into the lake below.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:01.44,0:18:07.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但这种简单的顺序包含着深厚的道理\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But even this simple sequence contains a profound idea.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:09.60,0:18:12.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,事物永远是以相同地顺序发展的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Events always happen in the same order.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:12.40,0:18:16.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,他们不会跳跃 也不会回头\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}They're never jumbled up and they never go backwards.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:32.84,0:18:36.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,你永远也不会看到它们反过来运行\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now that's something that you would never see in reverse.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:36.24,0:18:41.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但有趣的是 从来没有任何一条\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But, interestingly, there's nothing in the laws of physics that describe how all those
Dialogue: 0,0:18:41.76,0:18:45.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,描述水分子运动的物理定律规定\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}water molecules are moving around that prevent them
Dialogue: 0,0:18:45.04,0:18:48.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些水分子不能从湖面上\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}from all getting together on the surface of the lake,
Dialogue: 0,0:18:48.40,0:18:52.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一跃而起 冻结在一起 变成一块冰\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}jumping out of the water, sticking together into a block of ice
Dialogue: 0,0:18:52.36,0:18:56.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然后粘回冰川的前沿\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and then gluing themselves back on to the surface of the glacier again.
Dialogue: 0,0:18:56.56,0:18:58.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但有意思的是\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But, interestingly,
Dialogue: 0,0:18:58.60,0:19:03.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们能够理解为什么这一切不会倒转\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we do understand why the world doesn't run in reverse.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:03.64,0:19:05.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是有原因的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}There is a reason.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:05.36,0:19:08.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们有科学的解释\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We have a scientific explanation.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:08.00,0:19:11.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,叫做“时间箭头”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it's called the arrow of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:21.56,0:19:24.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们绝不会看到浪花穿过湖面 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We never see waves travelling across lakes,
Dialogue: 0,0:19:24.92,0:19:28.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,聚合在一起 变回冰川上的一部分\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}coming together and bouncing chunks of ice back onto glaciers.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:31.16,0:19:35.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们被迫走向未来\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We are compelled to travel into the future.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:35.64,0:19:40.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是因为 时间箭头决定了当时间流逝\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that's because the arrow of time dictates that as each moment passes,
Dialogue: 0,0:19:40.60,0:19:42.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一切都要改变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}things change.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:42.24,0:19:46.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而一旦变化发生 就绝没有回头的可能\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And once these changes have happened, they are never undone.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:51.44,0:19:56.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,永恒的变化 对我们人类有着根本性的意义\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Permanent change is a fundamental part of what it means to be human.
Dialogue: 0,0:19:56.92,0:20:00.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着时间流逝 我们慢慢老去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We all age as the years pass by.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:00.48,0:20:04.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,人们出生 成长 然后死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}People are born, they live, they die.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:04.24,0:20:08.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我觉得 这就是生命中必须承受的悲喜的一部分\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I suppose it's part of the joy and tragedy of our lives.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:08.72,0:20:11.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但在宇宙中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But out there in the universe,
Dialogue: 0,0:20:11.20,0:20:16.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,似乎所有的史诗般的周期 看上去是那么永恒不朽\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}those grand and epic cycles appear eternal and unchanging.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:16.36,0:20:18.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但这只是错觉\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But that's an illusion.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:18.08,0:20:21.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,其实 宇宙的生命 就和我们的生命一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You see, in the life of the universe, just as in our lives,
Dialogue: 0,0:20:21.56,0:20:26.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一切都在不可逆转地改变着\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}everything is irreversibly changing.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:35.24,0:20:37.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,通过一次次的改变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}By building change upon change,
Dialogue: 0,0:20:37.80,0:20:42.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间箭头推动着整个宇宙的演变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the arrow of time drives the evolution of the entire Universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:43.80,0:20:47.66,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当我们细细观察宇宙深处的时候 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And as we look out deep into the cosmos,
Dialogue: 0,0:20:47.66,0:20:49.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就能看出一些端倪\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we can see that story unfold.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:52.80,0:20:59.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是一张狮子座里很小一片夜空的图像\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is an image of a tiny piece of night sky in the constellation of Leo.
Dialogue: 0,0:20:59.72,0:21:02.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,其实也就是在狮子嘴附近的一小块\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's actually where the mouth of the lion would be.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:02.52,0:21:04.89,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然看上去很稀松平常 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And, despite appearances,
Dialogue: 0,0:21:04.89,0:21:10.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,不过这在近年来的天文史里 算是重量级的图像了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it is one of the most interesting images taken in recent astronomical history.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:10.48,0:21:14.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,有趣的东西就是这个小小的红点\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The interesting thing is this little red blob here,
Dialogue: 0,0:21:14.84,0:21:17.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,看上去很是平常\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}which looks very unremarkable.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:17.64,0:21:21.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但其实 这个红点\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But what that red blob is is the afterglow
Dialogue: 0,0:21:21.56,0:21:24.42,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是一次巨大的天体爆炸的余辉 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of an enormous cosmic explosion.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:24.42,0:21:26.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这显示的是一颗恒星的死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's the death of a star.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:26.88,0:21:28.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这颗恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That was about...
Dialogue: 0,0:21:28.56,0:21:33.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,大约是我们的太阳的40到50倍重\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}40 or even 50 times the mass of our sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:38.44,0:21:42.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它叫做GRB 090423 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Poetically named GRB 090423,
Dialogue: 0,0:21:42.28,0:21:45.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,曾经是一颗沃尔夫-拉叶型星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it was once a Wolf-Rayet star.
Dialogue: 0,0:21:42.28,0:21:46.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}沃尔夫-拉叶型星：简称白巨星，白超巨星\N是一种在正在演化的大质量恒星
Dialogue: 0,0:21:50.84,0:21:54.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然被快速旋转的气体星云遮蔽\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Shrouded by rapidly swirling clouds of gas,
Dialogue: 0,0:21:54.32,0:21:58.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它依然我们的太阳还要亮一万倍\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it burned 10,000 times more brightly than our sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:00.92,0:22:05.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但正是因为如此之亮 它的寿命极端的短 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But because it burned so brightly, it was extremely short-lived.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:08.40,0:22:11.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当它死亡时 巨大的恒星向内心坍塌\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As it died, the giant star collapsed in on itself.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:11.80,0:22:15.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这导致大量的光线与恒星物质\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That caused massive jets of light and stellar material
Dialogue: 0,0:22:15.96,0:22:18.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从它的两级喷射而出\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to be ejected from its poles,
Dialogue: 0,0:22:18.20,0:22:23.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这次爆炸闪烁的光芒 是太阳的一亿亿倍\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in an explosion that shone with the light of 10 million billion suns.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:30.24,0:22:34.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这场浩劫的余辉\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it's the afterglow of this catastrophic explosion
Dialogue: 0,0:22:34.24,0:22:38.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在我们的星球上看来 只是一个淡淡的小红点\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that is just visible from this planet as a faint red dot.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:44.40,0:22:49.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但这不是GRB 090423最有意思的地方\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But that's not what's so interesting about GRB 090423.
Dialogue: 0,0:22:49.36,0:22:54.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当我们仰望星空 看那些遥远的星星与星系时\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You see, when we look up into the sky, at distant stars and galaxies,
Dialogue: 0,0:22:54.48,0:22:57.65,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,其实看到的是过去的景象 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}then we're looking back in time
Dialogue: 0,0:22:57.65,0:23:00.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为光的运行也需要时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because the light takes time to journey from them to us.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:00.56,0:23:05.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而这个红点的光线传到我们眼里所花费的时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And the light from that red dot has been travelling to us
Dialogue: 0,0:23:05.20,0:23:09.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,几乎是整个宇宙的历史那么长\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}for almost the entire history of the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:09.16,0:23:14.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,其实 我们看到的这个事件\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You see, what we're looking at here is an event that happened
Dialogue: 0,0:23:14.08,0:23:15.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,早在130亿年前就发生了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}13 billion years ago.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:15.96,0:23:20.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,那时 大爆炸刚刚发生了6千万年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That's only about 600 million years after the Big Bang.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:20.20,0:23:22.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是宇宙刚刚形成了6千万年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}After the universe began.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:22.04,0:23:26.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所以 这算得上是宇宙最早期的历史了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So this is something incredibly early in the universe's history.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:26.80,0:23:33.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,实际上 它是我们能够观测到最早的物体\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In fact, this is the oldest single object that we've ever seen.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:33.56,0:23:37.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这个红点 是宇宙中第一批恒星的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}What we're looking at here is the explosive death
Dialogue: 0,0:23:37.20,0:23:40.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,爆炸和死亡历程\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of one of the first stars in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:23:53.04,0:23:58.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着宇宙的不断演化 会进入不同的时期\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As it evolves, the universe passes through distinct eras.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:00.16,0:24:03.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些宏大的纪元 它们的开始和结束\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Vast ages, whose beginnings and endings
Dialogue: 0,0:24:03.80,0:24:06.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都有着独特的里程碑\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}are marked by unique milestones.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:08.12,0:24:12.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,那就是一个个奇迹的诞生和消亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The births and deaths of its wonders.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:18.08,0:24:22.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,第一批恒星的诞生 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The moment the first stars were born is one of the most important changes
Dialogue: 0,0:24:22.76,0:24:24.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是茫茫宇宙史上的浓重一笔\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in the evolution of the cosmos.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:27.52,0:24:30.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它标志着宇宙原始期的结束\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It signals the end of the Primordial Era
Dialogue: 0,0:24:27.52,0:24:31.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}原始期：宇宙五纪元中的第一个
Dialogue: 0,0:24:30.36,0:24:36.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,以及第二个宇宙纪元的开始\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and marks the beginning of the second great age of the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:36.76,0:24:39.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是我们生活的这个时代\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The time in which we live.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:39.00,0:24:42.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它叫做“造星期”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The Stelliferous Era -
Dialogue: 0,0:24:42.44,0:24:44.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是众星璀璨的纪元\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the age of the stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:50.28,0:24:56.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,恒星不光点缀了夜空 还带来了我们的白昼\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Starlight illuminates the night sky and starlight illuminates our days.
Dialogue: 0,0:24:56.20,0:25:01.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳就是银河系中2000亿颗恒星之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our sun is just one of 200 billion stars in our galaxy.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:01.36,0:25:06.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而银河系 又是我们能观测到的1000亿个星系之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our galaxy is one of 100 billion in the observable Universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:06.64,0:25:11.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,仿佛在浩瀚的海洋中 有无数星星的岛屿一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And countless islands of countless stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:23.68,0:25:27.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,尽管宇宙的寿命已经超过了130亿年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Although the universe is over 13 billion years old,
Dialogue: 0,0:25:27.12,0:25:31.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们依然生活在造星期的众星之间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we still live close to the stars of the Stelliferous Era.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:31.32,0:25:36.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这个纪元的宇宙 美不胜收 多姿多彩 令人惊叹\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's an age of astonishing beauty and complexity in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:40.44,0:25:43.42,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙中充满了恒星 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The cosmos is absolutely awash with stars
Dialogue: 0,0:25:43.43,0:25:48.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,还有伴随它们的无数星云和行星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}surrounded by nebulae and systems of planets.
Dialogue: 0,0:25:48.08,0:25:53.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些数不胜数的世界 我们永远也探索不完\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Countless billions of worlds that we've yet to explore.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:00.12,0:26:04.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 宇宙并非一潭死水 毫无变化\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But the cosmos isn't static and unchanging.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:04.52,0:26:07.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它不会永远是这个样子\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It won't always be this way.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:07.44,0:26:11.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为在时间的雕琢之下\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because, as the arrow of time plays out,
Dialogue: 0,0:26:11.72,0:26:16.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙的美是动态的 变幻的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it produces a universe that is as dynamic as it's beautiful.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:23.40,0:26:27.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们目睹了恒星的诞生 也目睹了它们的死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We've seen stars born and we've seen stars die.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:27.48,0:26:31.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们知道 时间一去就不复返\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And we know that tomorrow won't be the same as today
Dialogue: 0,0:26:31.76,0:26:34.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为时间箭头告诉我们\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because the arrow of time says
Dialogue: 0,0:26:34.88,0:26:38.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,未来和过去是绝然不同的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the future will always be different from the past.
Dialogue: 0,0:26:40.36,0:26:42.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但这变化又因何而起？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But what drives this evolution?
Dialogue: 0,0:26:42.72,0:26:48.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,过去和未来 它们为何会有不同？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Why is there a difference between the past and the future?
Dialogue: 0,0:26:48.44,0:26:51.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间箭头的意义何在？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Why is there an arrow of time at all?
Dialogue: 0,0:27:13.00,0:27:17.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们每个人都对时间有着清晰的感觉\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We all have an intuitive understanding of the arrow of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:27:21.92,0:27:25.29,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,对于我们来说 斗转星移 昨日不再 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It seems obvious to us that things change
Dialogue: 0,0:27:25.29,0:27:27.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些都再自然不过了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the future will be different to the past.
Dialogue: 0,0:27:33.24,0:27:38.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是因为年复一年 我们见证了时间的作用\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}We know that because we see the effects of the passing years all around us.
Dialogue: 0,0:27:48.68,0:27:51.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里是卡曼斯科 一处废弃的钻石矿业城镇\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is Kolmanskop, an abandoned diamond mining town
Dialogue: 0,0:27:51.84,0:27:53.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它位于纳米比亚的南部\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in southern Namibia.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:02.56,0:28:05.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这座小镇建立于1908年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This entire town was founded in 1908,
Dialogue: 0,0:28:05.44,0:28:10.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当时 一位工人正在修建从吕德里茨港\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}when a worker who was building the railway from the port of Luderitz
Dialogue: 0,0:28:10.48,0:28:14.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,通向纳米比亚内地的铁路 他在这里的沙漠中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}inland into the centre of Namibia found a single diamond
Dialogue: 0,0:28:14.76,0:28:16.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,发现了一颗钻石\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}here in this desert.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:32.44,0:28:35.02,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在接下来的40年里 这里变成了一个\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}For 40 years, this was a
Dialogue: 0,0:28:35.02,0:28:37.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,人丁兴旺的社区 有一千多居民\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}thriving community of up to 1,000 people.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:37.16,0:28:39.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,人人都有机会一夜暴富 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}A place where you could become a millionaire,
Dialogue: 0,0:28:39.32,0:28:41.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,只要你能在这沙漠里找到钻石\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}picking diamonds out of the sand.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:46.04,0:28:49.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,财富滚滚而来 他们修建了豪华的住宅\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}While the money rolled in, they built grand houses
Dialogue: 0,0:28:49.20,0:28:52.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这苍茫的沙漠之中 享受着上流生活\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and lived a champagne lifestyle in the desert.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:55.32,0:28:59.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而当钻石被采掘一空 小镇随即被荒弃了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But when the diamonds dried up, the town was abandoned.
Dialogue: 0,0:28:59.32,0:29:02.69,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,又经过了半个世纪 这里的一切\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And for half a century it's fallen into disrepair
Dialogue: 0,0:29:02.70,0:29:06.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都已年久失修 正慢慢地回归沙漠\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as it's slowly reclaimed by the sands.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:22.80,0:29:28.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,Kolmanskop这里发生的一切 在宇宙里随处可见\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The processes at play here at Kolmanskop are happening everywhere in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:28.64,0:29:34.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为时间箭头理论的重点并不仅仅是“变化”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because it isn't simply permanent change that's central to the arrow of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:34.00,0:29:35.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而是“衰亡”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's decay.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:37.72,0:29:41.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 解释这一切的科学理论\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But the scientific explanation for why that is...
Dialogue: 0,0:29:43.08,0:29:47.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,并非来自人们对时间的探索\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}..didn't come from attempting to understand the effects of time in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:48.64,0:29:51.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而是来自于建造更快火车的努力\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It came from trying to build a faster train.
Dialogue: 0,0:29:54.56,0:30:00.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,19世纪 工程师们想尽各种办法提高蒸汽机的效率\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Back in the 19th century, engineers were concerned with the efficiency of steam engines.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:00.84,0:30:03.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,火该烧多热？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}How hot should the fire be?
Dialogue: 0,0:30:03.28,0:30:06.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,要用哪种物质的蒸汽？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}What substance should you boil in the steam engine?
Dialogue: 0,0:30:06.08,0:30:09.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是该用水 还是其他的什么？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Should it be water or something else?
Dialogue: 0,0:30:09.68,0:30:11.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这些都是至关重要的问题\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}These were profound questions.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:11.60,0:30:15.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而一个新的学科也应运而生 名叫热力学\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And out of those questions arose the science of thermodynamics.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:15.12,0:30:18.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是从那时开始 像热量 温度 能量这些概念\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's when concepts like heat and temperature and energy
Dialogue: 0,0:30:18.80,0:30:22.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,走进了科学的研究领域\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}entered the scientific vocabulary for the first time.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:22.04,0:30:26.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随之而来的 是一些更深层次的知识\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now, along with that deeper understanding
Dialogue: 0,0:30:26.40,0:30:30.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这也许是最关键的一条物理定律\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}emerged what is probably the most important law of physics
Dialogue: 0,0:30:30.32,0:30:35.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它能让我们理解时间的推移和宇宙的演化\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}for understanding the evolution of the universe and the passage of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:35.76,0:30:39.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它的名字是“热力学第二定律”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's called the Second Law of Thermodynamics.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:44.48,0:30:47.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这条定律意义非凡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The reason the Second Law of Thermodynamics was so profound
Dialogue: 0,0:30:47.80,0:30:53.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为它的核心 是一个标新立异的概念\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}was because, at its heart, it contained a radically new concept.
Dialogue: 0,0:30:53.32,0:30:57.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是物理学家们常说的“熵”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Something physicists call "entropy".
Dialogue: 0,0:30:59.72,0:31:01.25,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,熵的概念能够解释 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Entropy explains why,
Dialogue: 0,0:31:01.25,0:31:03.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,为什么在没有外力干预的情况下\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}left to the mercy of the elements,
Dialogue: 0,0:31:03.64,0:31:08.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,墙壁会断裂 玻璃会破碎 房屋会坍倒\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}mortar crumbles, glass shatters and buildings collapse.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:12.40,0:31:15.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,要想理解熵的概念 我们不能把物体\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And a good way to understand how is to think of objects
Dialogue: 0,0:31:15.12,0:31:16.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,看作是一个单一的东西\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}not as single things,
Dialogue: 0,0:31:16.68,0:31:20.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而要认识到它由许多部分组成\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}but as being made up of many constituent parts.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:20.12,0:31:24.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就像组成这沙堆的沙粒\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Like the individual grains that make up this pile of sand.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:27.60,0:31:31.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,熵 就是沙堆在保持原样的同时\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now, entropy is a measure of how many ways I can rearrange those grains
Dialogue: 0,0:31:31.88,0:31:35.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,能够被重新组织的可能性\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and still keep the sand pile the same.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:35.40,0:31:39.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当然 对于这个沙堆来说 可能性是无穷无尽的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And there are trillions and trillions and trillions of ways of doing that.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:39.76,0:31:45.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,无论我对这个沙堆做了什么 搅和它 移动它\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I mean, pretty much anything I do to this sand pile, if I mess the sand around and move it around,
Dialogue: 0,0:31:45.56,0:31:48.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它依然保持着刚才的形状和结构\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}then it doesn't change the shape or the structure at all.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:48.88,0:31:52.43,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,用熵来说 就是这个沙堆有很高的熵值 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So, in the language of entropy, this sand pile has high entropy
Dialogue: 0,0:31:52.43,0:31:55.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为我有很多方法重新组织它\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because there are many, many ways
Dialogue: 0,0:31:55.00,0:31:59.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而它的结构保持不变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that I can rearrange its constituents and not change it.
Dialogue: 0,0:31:59.56,0:32:04.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,那现在我来为宇宙造出点秩序\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now let me create some order in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:11.08,0:32:15.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这座小沙堡里 沙粒的数目\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Now, there are approximately as many sand grains in this sandcastle
Dialogue: 0,0:32:15.84,0:32:18.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,和这个沙堆应该差不多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as there are in the sand pile.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:18.64,0:32:22.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但是现在 无论我对它做什么\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But now, virtually anything I do to it will mess it up,
Dialogue: 0,0:32:22.04,0:32:26.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,几乎都会破坏它的结构和秩序\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will remove the beautiful order from this structure.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:26.76,0:32:30.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因此 这座沙堡熵值很低\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And because of that, the sandcastle has a low entropy.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:30.00,0:32:32.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是一种有序得多的状态\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's a much more ordered state.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:32.24,0:32:35.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,总的来说 如果有多种重组沙粒的方式\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So many ways of rearranging the sand grains
Dialogue: 0,0:32:35.72,0:32:39.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,又能保持结构 那么熵值就高\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}without changing the structure, high entropy.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:39.56,0:32:42.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如果重组这些沙粒\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Very few ways of rearranging the sand grains
Dialogue: 0,0:32:42.48,0:32:48.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而不破坏结构的可能性小 那么熵值就低\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}without changing the structure, without disordering it, low entropy.
Dialogue: 0,0:32:56.88,0:33:00.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,试想我把这沙堡扔在这一整天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Imagine I was to leave this castle in the desert all day.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:00.36,0:33:02.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,接下来的事情可想而知\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Then it's obvious what's going to happen.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:02.88,0:33:06.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,沙漠中的风会把沙子吹走\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The desert winds are going to blow the sand around
Dialogue: 0,0:33:06.16,0:33:10.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这座沙堡将会瓦解\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and this castle is going to disintegrate.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:10.00,0:33:13.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它的有序度会降低 最后又变回沙土\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Is going to become less ordered. Is going to fall to bits.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:16.92,0:33:20.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但从最根本的层面上思考一下\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But think about what's happening on the fundamental level.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:20.24,0:33:24.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,你看 风会带走沙堡的沙子\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}I mean, the wind is taking the sand off the castle
Dialogue: 0,0:33:24.08,0:33:28.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,把它们吹走 变成沙堆\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and blowing it over there somewhere and making a sand pile.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:28.80,0:33:31.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 没有一条物理定律规定\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}There's nothing fundamental in the laws of physics
Dialogue: 0,0:33:31.72,0:33:36.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,风不能从这里卷起沙子\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that says that the wind couldn't pick up some sand from over here,
Dialogue: 0,0:33:36.68,0:33:38.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,吹到这儿\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}deposit it here
Dialogue: 0,0:33:38.40,0:33:42.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然后精确地堆积成沙堡的形状\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and deposit it in precisely the shape of a sandcastle.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:42.12,0:33:48.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,理论上 风完全能够自发地把沙丘吹成沙堡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In principle, the wind could spontaneously build a sandcastle out of a pile of sand.
Dialogue: 0,0:33:59.40,0:34:01.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这种事情并非绝无可能\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}There's no reason why that couldn't happen.
Dialogue: 0,0:34:01.36,0:34:05.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而只是可能性微乎其微\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's just extremely, extremely unlikely because there
Dialogue: 0,0:34:05.48,0:34:10.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为把沙粒堆积成沙堡的方法少之又少\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}are very few ways of organising this sand so that it looks like a castle.
Dialogue: 0,0:34:17.16,0:34:19.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而最有可能发生的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's overwhelmingly more likely
Dialogue: 0,0:34:19.24,0:34:21.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就是当风卷起沙粒时\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that when the wind blows the sand around
Dialogue: 0,0:34:21.80,0:34:25.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,会把低熵值的沙堡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it will take the low entropy structure of the castle
Dialogue: 0,0:34:25.24,0:34:29.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,变成一个高熵值的沙堆\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and turn it into a high entropy structure, the sand pile.
Dialogue: 0,0:34:37.16,0:34:41.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所以 熵值永远在增加 究其原因\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So, entropy always increases. Why is that?
Dialogue: 0,0:34:41.96,0:34:45.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就是因为高熵值的状态拥有更高的概率\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because it's overwhelmingly more likely that it will.
Dialogue: 0,0:34:55.80,0:34:57.58,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,不可思议的是 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It seems incredible that
Dialogue: 0,0:34:57.58,0:35:02.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这条规定“风不会自动堆出沙堡”的定律\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}a law that says that sandcastles don't spontaneously form on the wind
Dialogue: 0,0:35:02.16,0:35:05.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,解开了物理学最深的谜团\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}could solve one of the deepest mysteries in physics.
Dialogue: 0,0:35:08.76,0:35:11.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,凭借着“熵增法则”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But by saying entropy always increases,
Dialogue: 0,0:35:11.24,0:35:15.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,热力学第二定律解释了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the Second Law of Thermodynamics is able to explain
Dialogue: 0,0:35:15.40,0:35:18.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间为何只有一个行进方向\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}why time only runs in one direction.
Dialogue: 0,0:35:34.64,0:35:38.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,对我来说 热力学第二定律体现了物理学\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The Second Law of Thermodynamics, for me, demonstrates everything
Dialogue: 0,0:35:38.20,0:35:42.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,优雅而强大的一面\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that's powerful and beautiful and profound about physics.
Dialogue: 0,0:35:42.80,0:35:45.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这条科学定律最开始是用来描述\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You see, here's a law that entered science
Dialogue: 0,0:35:45.00,0:35:47.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,热量的传导方式\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as a way of talking about how heat moves around
Dialogue: 0,0:35:47.48,0:35:49.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,以及蒸汽机效率的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the efficiency of steam engines.
Dialogue: 0,0:35:49.60,0:35:57.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最终它却解释了物理史上最大的谜题之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But it ended up being able to explain one of the great mysteries in the history of science.
Dialogue: 0,0:35:57.04,0:36:00.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,为什么过去和未来存在区别？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Why is there a difference between the past and the future?
Dialogue: 0,0:36:00.80,0:36:07.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为第二定律说 万事都从有序趋于无序\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You see, the second law says that everything tends from order to disorder.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:07.68,0:36:12.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,过去和未来的区别就在于此\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}That means that there is a difference between the past and future.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:12.16,0:36:14.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,过去的宇宙是更有序的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In the past, the universe was more ordered.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:14.64,0:36:18.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而未来的宇宙 有序度只会越来越低\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In the future, the universe will be less ordered.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:18.20,0:36:21.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就意味着 时间的行进是有方向的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that means there's a direction to the passage of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:21.76,0:36:27.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所以 热力学第二定律\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So the Second Law of Thermodynamics has introduced the concept
Dialogue: 0,0:36:27.32,0:36:30.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,引入了“时间箭头”的概念\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of an arrow of time into science.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:38.24,0:36:40.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,自从矿场1954年被废弃之后 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The arrow of time has been playing out in Kolmanskop
Dialogue: 0,0:36:40.76,0:36:45.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一去不复返的时间箭头 消磨着Kolmanskop的一切\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}since the mining facility was abandoned in 1954.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:48.28,0:36:53.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而在宇宙中 这样的过程已经持续了140亿年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But in the universe, it's been playing out for almost 14 billion years.
Dialogue: 0,0:36:53.44,0:36:56.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也将为我们带来深远的影响\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it will have profound consequences.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:04.40,0:37:07.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为它意味着恒星不能永远燃烧下去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because it means stars cannot shine forever.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:07.88,0:37:12.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当然 我们太阳系中心的那颗恒星亦是如此\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Including the star at the centre of our solar system.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:14.88,0:37:19.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在它的晚年 太阳不会简单地慢慢黯淡下去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}At the end of its life, the sun won't simply fade away to nothing.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:22.64,0:37:27.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当太阳的燃料耗尽时 它的核心会坍缩\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As it begins to run out of fuel, its core will collapse
Dialogue: 0,0:37:27.28,0:37:29.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而坍缩过程中产生的热量\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the extra heat this generates
Dialogue: 0,0:37:29.40,0:37:31.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,又会导致它的外层膨胀\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will cause its outer layers to expand.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:39.12,0:37:41.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这个持续十亿年的过程\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In around a billion years' time,
Dialogue: 0,0:37:41.36,0:37:45.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,将给我们脆弱的世界带来毁灭性的后果\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}this will have a catastrophic effect on our fragile world.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:52.32,0:37:55.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,地球将会慢慢地变热\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Gradually, the Earth will become hotter and hotter.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:55.48,0:37:59.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是说 地球的好日子终有到头的时候\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So there will be one last perfect day on Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:37:59.48,0:38:05.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最终 这个星球上所有的生命都将无法生存\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But eventually the existence of all life on this planet will become impossible.
Dialogue: 0,0:38:09.60,0:38:14.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在生命绝迹之后很长时间 太阳会变得非常大\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Long after a life has disappeared, the sun will have grown so much
Dialogue: 0,0:38:14.04,0:38:16.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它将充满整个地平线\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it will fill the entire horizon.
Dialogue: 0,0:38:23.08,0:38:24.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它将会变成红巨星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It will become a red giant.
Dialogue: 0,0:38:24.92,0:38:27.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是太阳生命的最后阶段\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The last phase of its life.
Dialogue: 0,0:38:37.72,0:38:39.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们的星球很难在这一时期幸存下来\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our planet might not survive to this point.
Dialogue: 0,0:38:39.92,0:38:45.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但即使幸存了 剩下的也不过是一块被烧焦的废石\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But, if it does, little more than a scorched and barren rock will remain
Dialogue: 0,0:38:45.84,0:38:49.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,见证着太阳的最后毁灭\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to witness the final death throes of our star.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:00.08,0:39:04.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,60亿年之后 我们的太阳将爆炸\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In six billion years, our sun will explode.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:04.32,0:39:08.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,将大量的气体与尘埃抛洒到太空中 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Throwing vast amounts of gas and dust out into space,
Dialogue: 0,0:39:08.56,0:39:10.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,形成一个巨大星云\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to form a gigantic nebula.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:18.48,0:39:20.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而它的核心散发着微弱热量 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And at its heart will beat
Dialogue: 0,0:39:20.76,0:39:22.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如一片记录过往的琥珀\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}a faintly glowing ember.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:22.52,0:39:26.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,诉说着它辉煌夺目的过去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}All that remains of our once magnificent sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:26.04,0:39:28.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,那时 太阳的尺寸将会比地球还小\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It will be smaller than the size of the Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:28.80,0:39:31.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是不到现在太阳体积的百万分之一 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Less than a millionth of its current volume
Dialogue: 0,0:39:31.88,0:39:34.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而亮度与现在相比更是微不足道\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and a fraction of its brightness.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:34.28,0:39:37.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们的太阳将变成一颗白矮星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our sun will have become a white dwarf.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:46.76,0:39:49.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,由于没有燃料可以燃烧\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}With no fuel left to burn,
Dialogue: 0,0:39:49.04,0:39:55.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,白矮星微弱的亮光来自于它早年的余热\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}a white dwarf's faint glow comes from the last residual heat from its extinguished furnace.
Dialogue: 0,0:39:58.44,0:40:00.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳死了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The sun is now dead.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:00.28,0:40:05.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它在冰冷宇宙的深处 慢慢地散失掉最后一丝光热\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Its remains slowly cooling in the freezing temperatures of deep space.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:10.00,0:40:12.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,若从地球的位置望去\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Looking at it from where the Earth is now,
Dialogue: 0,0:40:12.80,0:40:17.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这时太阳放出的光 只和晴朗夜空里的满月相当\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it would only generate the same amount of light as the full moon on a clear night.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:23.24,0:40:27.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳的命运 和其他所有恒星是一样的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The fate of the sun IS the same as for all stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:27.48,0:40:31.23,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,总有一天 所有的恒星都将死亡 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}One day, they must all eventually die
Dialogue: 0,0:40:31.23,0:40:34.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙会陷入无休止的漫漫长夜\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the cosmos will be plunged into eternal night.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:34.48,0:40:39.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这就是时光不可倒流的结果\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And this is the most profound consequence of the arrow of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:39.28,0:40:42.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为我们居住的宇宙\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because this structured universe that we inhabit,
Dialogue: 0,0:40:42.32,0:40:46.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,和其中的所有奇观 恒星 行星 以及星云\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and all its wonders - the stars, the planets and the galaxies -
Dialogue: 0,0:40:46.60,0:40:49.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都无法永存\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}cannot last forever.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:49.16,0:40:54.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙最终将会慢慢凋零 死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The cosmos will eventually fade and die.
Dialogue: 0,0:40:57.80,0:41:00.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,首先到来的是造星期的终结\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}First will come the end of the Stelliferous Era.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:00.60,0:41:03.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,万星增辉的纪元就此结束\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The end of the age of starlight.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:08.00,0:41:11.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最大的恒星最先消失\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The largest stars are the first to disappear,
Dialogue: 0,0:41:11.08,0:41:13.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,猛烈地坍缩成为黑洞\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}violently collapsing into black holes.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:13.80,0:41:16.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它们的寿命通常只有几百万年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Just a few million years after their formation.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:19.40,0:41:21.99,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但在这些大型恒星消亡后很久 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But long after they're gone,
Dialogue: 0,0:41:21.99,0:41:23.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,只有一种恒星还留存着\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}just one type of star will remain.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:27.24,0:41:31.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这张照片显示的 就是离我们太阳系最近的恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is a picture of the nearest star to our solar system,
Dialogue: 0,0:41:31.40,0:41:32.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,比邻星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Proxima Centauri.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:31.40,0:41:35.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}比邻星：半人马座α三合星的第三颗星
Dialogue: 0,0:41:32.88,0:41:36.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它离我们只不过4.2光年而已 而这颗恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's only 4.2 lightyears away. But the reason it doesn't stand out
Dialogue: 0,0:41:36.96,0:41:39.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,并不比远处的其他星星明亮多少\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}against the much more distant stars in this photograph
Dialogue: 0,0:41:39.88,0:41:43.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是因为比邻星异常微小\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is that Proxima Centauri is incredibly tiny.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:43.68,0:41:46.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这类恒星叫做红矮星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's a kind of star known as a red dwarf star.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:46.48,0:41:50.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它的质量只有太阳的11%到12%\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's only about 11-12% the mass of our sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:50.36,0:41:56.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在我们看来 它的亮度只是太阳的一万八千分之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But to our eyes it would appear to shine 18,000 times less brightly.
Dialogue: 0,0:41:58.36,0:42:02.15,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但红矮星与那些比它大得多 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But red dwarfs do have one advantage
Dialogue: 0,0:42:02.15,0:42:06.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,亮得多的星星相比 有一个优势\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}over their much more luminous and magnificent stellar brethren.
Dialogue: 0,0:42:06.24,0:42:09.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为它们很小\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that's because they're so small,
Dialogue: 0,0:42:09.80,0:42:13.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,能以极慢的速度消耗核燃料\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}they burn their nuclear fuel incredibly slowly,
Dialogue: 0,0:42:13.20,0:42:16.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,所以它们的寿命能达到万亿年之久\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}so they have lifespans of trillions of years.
Dialogue: 0,0:42:16.36,0:42:20.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这意味着 像比邻星这样的恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that means that stars like Proxima Centauri
Dialogue: 0,0:42:20.08,0:42:24.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,会在宇宙里坚持到最后\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will be the last living stars in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:42:29.00,0:42:33.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如果我们能够存活到那么久的话\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}If we survive into the far future of the universe,
Dialogue: 0,0:42:33.76,0:42:38.74,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们的后代很有可能会将他们的文明\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}then it's possible to imagine our distant descendants
Dialogue: 0,0:42:38.74,0:42:41.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,建立在红矮星附近\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}building their civilisation around red dwarfs
Dialogue: 0,0:42:41.24,0:42:46.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,以获取最后一丝仅存的光热\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to capture the energy from those last fading embers of stars,
Dialogue: 0,0:42:46.48,0:42:51.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就像我们的祖先在寒冷的冬夜\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}just as our ancestors crowded around campfires
Dialogue: 0,0:42:51.20,0:42:54.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,围绕在营火边取暖一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}for warmth on cold winter's nights.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:13.12,0:43:16.50,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,比邻星燃烧得这么慢的原因 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The reason why Proxima Centauri burns so slowly
Dialogue: 0,0:43:16.50,0:43:19.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,是它的体积和引力都很小\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is because its small size and low gravity
Dialogue: 0,0:43:19.36,0:43:23.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这意味着它内核的压力比那些更大的恒星要小很多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}mean its core is under much lower pressure than larger stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:25.88,0:43:29.86,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也意味着它的内核会不停地流动 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This also means that its interior is constantly churning,
Dialogue: 0,0:43:29.86,0:43:32.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,并不断地从表面喷出来\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}whipping up the surface into a fiery turmoil.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:35.96,0:43:38.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然比邻星那么昏暗 它的表面\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Explosive solar flares occur almost continually,
Dialogue: 0,0:43:38.76,0:43:41.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,却在永无休止地发生着爆炸性的耀斑\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}even though it burns so dimly.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:43.48,0:43:48.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但最终 比邻星也会死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But Proxima Centauri will eventually die.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:48.36,0:43:52.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,和我们的太阳相同 它也会变成一颗白矮星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And like our sun, it too will become a white dwarf.
Dialogue: 0,0:43:53.56,0:43:57.47,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当造星季临近结束 一切都将黯淡下去 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As the age of starlight ends,
Dialogue: 0,0:43:57.47,0:44:00.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙里只剩下最微弱的几丝亮光\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}all but the dimmest flicker of light in the universe will go out.
Dialogue: 0,0:44:00.52,0:44:05.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,白矮星的幽光 将用它最后一抹亮色\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The faint glow of white dwarfs will provide the only illumination
Dialogue: 0,0:44:05.88,0:44:12.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,照耀着这个充斥着死亡恒星和黑洞的宇宙\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in a dark and empty void, littered with dead stars and black holes.
Dialogue: 0,0:44:14.24,0:44:19.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,到这时 宇宙已有一万亿年的历史了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}By this point, the universe will be 100 trillion years old.
Dialogue: 0,0:44:22.92,0:44:26.14,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,然而 在它宏大的生命中 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And yet, even now, the vast majority of its lifespan
Dialogue: 0,0:44:26.14,0:44:29.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,绝大部分的旅程还尚未开始\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}still lies ahead of it.
Dialogue: 0,0:44:46.76,0:44:49.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在地球上的某些地方 人们可以隐隐感知到\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}There are few places on Earth where you can get an inkling
Dialogue: 0,0:44:49.92,0:44:53.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,遥远的未来会发生什么\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of what the far future has in store.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:06.56,0:45:08.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里是纳米比亚的骷髅海岸\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is Namibia's Skeleton Coast,
Dialogue: 0,0:45:08.56,0:45:11.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,南大西洋的冰冷海水\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}where the cold water to the South Atlantic
Dialogue: 0,0:45:11.56,0:45:13.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,和纳米布沙漠交汇于此\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}meet the Namib Desert.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:13.88,0:45:16.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里是地球上环境最恶劣的地方之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it is one of the most inhospitable places on Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:16.72,0:45:19.50,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,早在17世纪 葡萄牙的水手\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Back in the 17th century, Portuguese sailors
Dialogue: 0,0:45:19.50,0:45:22.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就把这里称为“地狱之门”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}used to call this place the gates to hell
Dialogue: 0,0:45:22.08,0:45:27.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为 几乎每天早上这里都笼罩在这种浓雾之中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because this dense fog that you see pretty much every morning along this coast,
Dialogue: 0,0:45:27.52,0:45:31.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,还有不断变换着形状的沙滩\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}coupled with the constantly shifting shape of the sandbanks,
Dialogue: 0,0:45:31.76,0:45:34.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,年复一年 成千上万的船只\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}meant that over the years, literally thousands of ships
Dialogue: 0,0:45:34.80,0:45:37.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在这条海岸线附近失事沉没\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}were wrecked along this coastline.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:43.32,0:45:46.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就算你挣扎着登上沙滩 问题还是接踵而至\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And even if you made it to shore, that wasn't the end of your problems
Dialogue: 0,0:45:46.80,0:45:49.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里的海流很是强劲\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because the currents are so strong here
Dialogue: 0,0:45:49.24,0:45:52.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一旦上岸 就再也没有可能回到海中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that there is no way of rowing back out to sea.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:52.00,0:45:57.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,往那边看 会看见绵延数百公里的荒凉沙漠\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}If you look that way, there's just hundreds of miles of inhospitable desert.
Dialogue: 0,0:45:59.76,0:46:04.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这里确实是有去无回的地狱\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}So, it genuinely was a place of no return.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:04.48,0:46:09.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如果船只在此沉没 人们绝无生还的可能\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}If you were shipwrecked here, this WAS the end of your universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:20.40,0:46:22.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是Edward Bohlen号\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is the Eduard Bohlen.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:22.36,0:46:25.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这条船曾经是条远洋轮船\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}She was once an ocean-going steamer,
Dialogue: 0,0:46:25.20,0:46:28.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在此地和欧洲之间航行 运送旅客和货物\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}ferrying passengers and cargo between here and Europe.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:32.60,0:46:37.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,1909年9月5日 它在一场大雾中搁浅\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}On 5th September, 1909, she ran aground in thick fog.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:43.92,0:46:47.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,跟所有在此沉没的船只一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Yet, like all the vessels wrecked along this shoreline,
Dialogue: 0,0:46:47.40,0:46:50.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它在水中慢慢被腐蚀殆尽的时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the time it takes her to decay to nothing
Dialogue: 0,0:46:50.24,0:46:52.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,要比它航行时间的总和长得多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will be far longer than her time at sea.
Dialogue: 0,0:46:57.96,0:47:00.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在宇宙遥远的未来中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In the far future of the cosmos,
Dialogue: 0,0:47:00.92,0:47:04.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,同样的命运也会落在剩下的白矮星身上\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}a similar destiny awaits the remaining white dwarfs.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:10.76,0:47:14.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,黑矮星将是这些末日之星的最终形态\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}A black dwarf will be the final fate of those last stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:14.36,0:47:17.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,异常冰冷的白矮星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}White dwarfs that have become so cold
Dialogue: 0,0:47:17.16,0:47:20.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,不会再散发出光和热\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that they barely emit any more heat or light.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:25.00,0:47:26.87,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,黑矮星是黑暗的荒凉星球 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Black dwarfs are dark,
Dialogue: 0,0:47:26.87,0:47:30.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,由高密度的简并态物质构成\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}dense decaying balls of degenerate matter.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:26.87,0:47:31.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}简并态物质：一种密度极高的物质
Dialogue: 0,0:47:30.48,0:47:33.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,大部分为恒星的遗骸\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Little more than the ashes of stars.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:34.84,0:47:39.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,构成它们的原子被高度压缩\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Their constituent atoms are so severely crushed
Dialogue: 0,0:47:39.08,0:47:44.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因此 黑矮星的密度要比我们的太阳大一百万倍\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that black dwarfs are a million times denser than our sun.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:44.16,0:47:47.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,恒星要变成黑矮星需要相当长的时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Stars take so long to reach this point,
Dialogue: 0,0:47:47.12,0:47:49.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在宇宙诞生140亿年后的今天\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that after nearly 14 billion years
Dialogue: 0,0:47:49.72,0:47:54.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们有理由相信 现在的宇宙中没有黑矮星存在\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we believe there are currently no black dwarfs in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:47:54.84,0:47:57.31,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,尽管还没有出现黑矮星 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But despite never seeing one,
Dialogue: 0,0:47:57.31,0:48:00.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们依然能预测出它们将如何消亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we can still predict how they will end their days.
Dialogue: 0,0:48:00.92,0:48:04.70,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就好像船体的铁板会慢慢锈蚀 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Just as the iron than makes up this ship
Dialogue: 0,0:48:04.70,0:48:08.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,随着沙漠中的罡风灰飞烟灭一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will eventually rust and be carried away by the desert winds,
Dialogue: 0,0:48:08.48,0:48:14.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,黑矮星上那些宇宙中最后的物质\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}so we think that the matter inside black dwarfs, the last matter in the universe,
Dialogue: 0,0:48:14.60,0:48:21.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,最终会挥发殆尽 在辐射中渐渐湮灭入无尽虚空\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will eventually evaporate away and be carried off into the void as radiation,
Dialogue: 0,0:48:21.72,0:48:25.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一点儿痕迹都不会留下\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}leaving absolutely nothing behind.
Dialogue: 0,0:48:34.56,0:48:36.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,黑矮星消逝之后 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}With the black dwarfs gone,
Dialogue: 0,0:48:36.32,0:48:39.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就再也没有一个物质的原子存在了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}there won't be a single atom of matter left.
Dialogue: 0,0:48:42.40,0:48:45.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一度多姿多彩的宇宙\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}All that will remain of our once rich cosmos
Dialogue: 0,0:48:45.84,0:48:49.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,只会剩下光子和黑洞\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will be particles of light and black holes.
Dialogue: 0,0:48:55.88,0:48:59.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,经过亿万年之后\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}After an unimaginable length of time,
Dialogue: 0,0:48:59.08,0:49:02.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就连黑洞也会湮灭\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}even the black holes will have evaporated
Dialogue: 0,0:49:02.56,0:49:06.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙中空无一物 只剩一片光子的海洋\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the universe will be nothing but a sea of photons,
Dialogue: 0,0:49:06.72,0:49:10.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,温度的差异也渐渐抹平\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}gradually tending towards the same temperature,
Dialogue: 0,0:49:10.20,0:49:14.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在宇宙膨胀的作用下 一切都会趋近于绝对零度\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as the expansion of the universe cools them towards absolute zero.
Dialogue: 0,0:49:10.20,0:49:14.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}绝对零度：即-273.15摄氏度
Dialogue: 0,0:49:23.16,0:49:26.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当我说到“亿万年”的时候 我真的指亿万年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And when I say "unimaginable period of time," I really mean it.
Dialogue: 0,0:49:26.52,0:49:33.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是10的100次方年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's 10,000 trillion trillion trillion trillion trillion trillion trillion trillion years.
Dialogue: 0,0:49:33.80,0:49:35.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,10的100次方有多大？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}How big's that number?
Dialogue: 0,0:49:35.76,0:49:41.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,如果一个原子代表一年\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}If I were to start counting with a single atom representing one year
Dialogue: 0,0:49:41.68,0:49:44.81,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,把我们宇宙中的所有原子都用上 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}then there wouldn't be enough atoms in the entire universe
Dialogue: 0,0:49:44.81,0:49:48.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也远远不够10的100次方那么多\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}to get anywhere near that number.
Dialogue: 0,0:49:54.84,0:50:00.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当我们宇宙中最后物质的残余都消失不见 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Once the very last remnants of the very last stars have finally decayed away to nothing,
Dialogue: 0,0:50:00.72,0:50:04.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,当整个宇宙都达到了相同温度\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and everything reaches the same temperature,
Dialogue: 0,0:50:04.68,0:50:08.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙的故事就要划上句号了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}the story of the universe finally comes to an end.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:12.80,0:50:18.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,那时 将是宇宙第一次能够永恒不变\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}For the first time in its life, the universe will be permanent and unchanging.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:18.16,0:50:21.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,熵值也终于停止增长 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Entropy finally stops increasing
Dialogue: 0,0:50:21.00,0:50:25.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为宇宙的无序度已经无法再增加\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because the cosmos cannot get any more disordered.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:25.28,0:50:29.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,没有什么发生 而且再也不会发生什么了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Nothing happens and it keeps not happening.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:29.68,0:50:31.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一直如此\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Forever.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:36.00,0:50:38.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这就是所谓的“宇宙热寂说”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's what's known as the heat death of the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:38.92,0:50:42.35,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,到那时 宇宙会永远地保持\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}An era when the cosmos will remain
Dialogue: 0,0:50:42.35,0:50:46.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,广阔 冰冷 荒凉沉寂的状态\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}vast and cold and desolate for the rest of time.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:46.08,0:50:49.97,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而到那时 过去 现在 和未来之间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But that's because there is no difference
Dialogue: 0,0:50:49.97,0:50:51.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,完全不再有区别\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}between the past, the present and the future.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:51.68,0:50:55.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,没有什么能够衡量时间的流逝\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}There's no way of measuring the passage of time
Dialogue: 0,0:50:55.08,0:50:58.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为宇宙永远保持原样 不再变化\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because nothing in the cosmos changes.
Dialogue: 0,0:50:58.16,0:51:02.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间箭头被永远地凝固了\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The arrow of time has simply ceased to exist.
Dialogue: 0,0:51:13.08,0:51:16.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这就是宇宙不可避免的宿命\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's an inescapable fact of the universe,
Dialogue: 0,0:51:16.32,0:51:19.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它早已写在了物理学的基本原理中\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}written into the fundamental laws of physics.
Dialogue: 0,0:51:19.88,0:51:22.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,宇宙终将死亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The entire cosmos will die.
Dialogue: 0,0:51:27.64,0:51:29.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在我们的银河系 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Every single one of the 200 billion stars
Dialogue: 0,0:51:29.45,0:51:33.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,2000亿颗恒星中的每一颗都难逃一死\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in our galaxy will go out.
Dialogue: 0,0:51:36.56,0:51:41.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳的消亡 意味着地球上生命的终结\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And just as the death of the sun means the end of life on our planet,
Dialogue: 0,0:51:41.16,0:51:43.89,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而每一颗恒星的消亡 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}so the death of every star
Dialogue: 0,0:51:43.89,0:51:47.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也都在抹煞着生命存在的可能性\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}will extinguish any possibility of life in the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:51:51.68,0:51:56.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,太阳最终会消亡 也会导致地球\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The fact that the sun will die and it will incinerate the Earth
Dialogue: 0,0:51:56.28,0:52:00.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,以及地球上一切生命的灭亡\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and obliterate all life on our planet in the process,
Dialogue: 0,0:52:00.16,0:52:02.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这听上去也许会让人感到悲观\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}might sound a bit depressing to you.
Dialogue: 0,0:52:02.84,0:52:04.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,你当然可以说 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}You might legitimately ask,
Dialogue: 0,0:52:04.32,0:52:08.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,“那为什么不构建一个完全不同的宇宙呢？\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}"Well, surely you could build a universe in a different way?
Dialogue: 0,0:52:08.36,0:52:11.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在那个宇宙中 一切不会归于混沌\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}"Surely you could build it so it didn't have to descend
Dialogue: 0,0:52:11.28,0:52:13.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这样不是很好吗？”\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}from order into chaos?"
Dialogue: 0,0:52:13.24,0:52:18.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,答案是 不 我们做不到 只要还想让生命存在 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Well, the answer is no, you couldn't, if you wanted life to exist in it.
Dialogue: 0,0:52:24.72,0:52:30.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,时间箭头 以及那些会导致宇宙灭亡的微小改变 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The arrow of time, the sequence of changes that slowly leads the universe to its death,
Dialogue: 0,0:52:30.36,0:52:35.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,其实恰恰是最初的生命缔造者\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is the very same thing that creates the conditions for life in the first place.
Dialogue: 0,0:52:40.28,0:52:42.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为 物质的形成需要时间 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because it takes time for matter to form
Dialogue: 0,0:52:42.56,0:52:48.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在重力作用下 行星和恒星的形成也需要时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and it takes time for gravity to pull it together into stars and planets.
Dialogue: 0,0:52:53.28,0:52:56.16,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,正是时间的箭头 在宇宙的青春期\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The arrow of time creates a bright window
Dialogue: 0,0:52:56.16,0:52:58.08,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,打开了一扇明亮的窗户\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}in the universe's adolescence.
Dialogue: 0,0:52:58.08,0:53:00.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从而使生命成为可能\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}During which, life is possible.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:07.88,0:53:11.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但这扇窗户并不会开得太久\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But it's a window that doesn't stay open for long.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:14.44,0:53:17.96,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,同宇宙的生命\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}As a fraction of the lifespan of the universe,
Dialogue: 0,0:53:17.96,0:53:23.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是从宇宙形成之初到最后一个黑洞湮灭 相比\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}as measured from its beginning to the evaporation of the last black hole,
Dialogue: 0,0:53:23.52,0:53:28.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们的生命只不过占了它的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}life, as we know it, is only possible for one thousandth
Dialogue: 0,0:53:28.80,0:53:32.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,10的86次方...\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of a billion billion billionth billion billion billionth
Dialogue: 0,0:53:32.28,0:53:35.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,...分之一\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}billion billion billionth of a per cent.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:37.64,0:53:44.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这就是为什么对我来说 宇宙的奇迹不是某颗恒星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that's why, for me, the most astonishing wonder of the universe isn't a star
Dialogue: 0,0:53:44.64,0:53:47.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,某颗行星 或某个星系\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}or a planet or a galaxy.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:47.28,0:53:49.60,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我认为 宇宙的奇迹不是某个东西\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It isn't a thing at all.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:49.60,0:53:52.52,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而是这时间长河里的须臾一瞬\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It's an instant in time.
Dialogue: 0,0:53:52.52,0:53:55.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也就是现在\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that time is now.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:03.36,0:54:07.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在永恒的时间里 人类出现在地球上的这段时间\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Humans have walked the Earth for just the smallest fraction
Dialogue: 0,0:54:07.72,0:54:11.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,只是微不足道的一小部分\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}of that briefest of moments in deep time.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:14.04,0:54:16.69,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然我们在地球上只生存了20万年 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But in our 200,000 years on this planet,
Dialogue: 0,0:54:16.69,0:54:19.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们却已经取得了令人惊叹的进步\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we've made remarkable progress.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:22.28,0:54:27.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,仅仅在2500年前 我们还认为太阳是天神\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}It was only 2,500 years ago that we believed that the sun was a god
Dialogue: 0,0:54:27.44,0:54:30.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们还在用建在山巅的石塔\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and measured its orbit with stone towers,
Dialogue: 0,0:54:30.28,0:54:32.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,来记录它的运行轨迹\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}built on the top of a hill.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:32.72,0:54:37.45,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,现在 人们的好奇不再局限于太阳神 \N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Today, the language of curiosity is not sun gods,
Dialogue: 0,0:54:37.45,0:54:39.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,而是转向了科学\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}but science.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:39.40,0:54:44.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,现代的天文台 与这13座塔相比\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And we have observatories that are almost infinitely more sophisticated
Dialogue: 0,0:54:44.24,0:54:49.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,简直要复杂无数倍 它们正在探索宇宙深处的奥秘\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}than the 13 towers, that can gaze out deep into the universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:54:52.28,0:54:55.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,也许更令人赞叹的是\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And, perhaps even more remarkably,
Dialogue: 0,0:54:55.24,0:54:57.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,通过先进的理论物理和数学\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}through theoretical physics and mathematics,
Dialogue: 0,0:54:57.88,0:55:03.04,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们可以计算出遥远的未来 宇宙将走向何方\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}we can calculate what the universe will look like in the distant future.
Dialogue: 0,0:55:03.04,0:55:08.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,甚至能透过严密的推算 清晰地看到它的终结\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And we can even make concrete predictions about its end.
Dialogue: 0,0:55:15.20,0:55:19.80,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我相信 只有通过对宇宙的不断探索\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And I believe it's only by continuing our explanation of the cosmos
Dialogue: 0,0:55:19.80,0:55:22.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,对自然规律的不断寻觅\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and the laws of nature that govern it,
Dialogue: 0,0:55:22.56,0:55:29.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们才能真正了解自己在宇宙奇迹中的具体位置\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}that we can truly understand ourselves and our place in this universe of wonders.
Dialogue: 0,0:55:33.16,0:55:38.24,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这也是我们这些地球居民短暂生命的意义所在\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And that's what we've done in our brief moment on Planet Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:55:41.76,0:55:45.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,1977年 “旅行者1号”探测器\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}In 1977, a space probe called Voyager 1
Dialogue: 0,0:55:45.12,0:55:49.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,开始了探索太阳系的征程\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}was launched on a grand tour of the solar system.
Dialogue: 0,0:55:49.28,0:55:52.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它先后抵达了气体巨行星木星\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And it visited the great gas giant planets -
Dialogue: 0,0:55:52.40,0:55:56.68,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,还有土星 在踏向茫茫宇宙之前\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Jupiter and Saturn - and made some wonderful discoveries
Dialogue: 0,0:55:56.68,0:56:00.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,做出了很多神奇的发现\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}before heading off towards interstellar space.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:02.24,0:56:06.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,13年后 当它的任务基本完成\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}13 years later, after its mission was almost over,
Dialogue: 0,0:56:06.76,0:56:12.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,它回头拍下了自己家园 太阳系的最后一张照片\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}it turned around and took one last picture of its home solar system.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:12.92,0:56:14.64,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,就是这张照片\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}This is that picture.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:17.08,0:56:20.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这张照片的精彩之处就在于\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And the beautiful thing about this picture
Dialogue: 0,0:56:20.92,0:56:24.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,一抹微弱的亮光\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is this single pixel of light
Dialogue: 0,0:56:24.20,0:56:26.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,悬浮在宇宙黑色的背景之上\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}suspended against the blackness of space.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:26.76,0:56:31.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为那抹亮光 那一个小点 就是我们地球\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Because that pixel, that point, is Planet Earth.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:31.36,0:56:34.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,这是一张我们星球最遥远的照片\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}The most distant picture of our planet ever taken.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:34.44,0:56:37.56,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,拍摄点距地球60亿公里远\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}6 billion kilometres away.
Dialogue: 0,0:56:47.00,0:56:51.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,虽然我觉得这张照片的科学价值有限\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And whilst I suppose it has very limited scientific value,
Dialogue: 0,0:56:51.00,0:56:54.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但是 正是这一抹亮光\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}for me, this tiny point of light
Dialogue: 0,0:56:54.00,0:57:01.44,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,才是人类特质最有力的证明\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is the most powerful and profound demonstration of perhaps the most human of qualities.
Dialogue: 0,0:57:01.44,0:57:06.32,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们拥有对宇宙 对家园\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Our unique ability to reflect on the universe's existence
Dialogue: 0,0:57:06.32,0:57:08.28,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,对世间万物的思考\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and our place within it.
Dialogue: 0,0:57:13.16,0:57:18.84,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,地球上的你我 都生存在这片小小的筏子上\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Just as we, and all life on Earth, stand on this tiny speck
Dialogue: 0,0:57:18.84,0:57:25.20,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在无限宇宙中 一切生命\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}adrift in infinite space, so life in the universe will only exist
Dialogue: 0,0:57:25.20,0:57:29.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都只是转瞬即逝的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}for a fleeting bright instance in time
Dialogue: 0,0:57:29.00,0:57:35.00,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为生命 跟那些恒星 行星 星系一样\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because life, just like the stars and the planets and the galaxies,
Dialogue: 0,0:57:35.00,0:57:40.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,都不过是从有序到混沌的宇宙旅程中的匆匆过客\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}is just a temporary structure on the long road from order to disorder.
Dialogue: 0,0:57:49.96,0:57:52.12,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,但是这并不意味着生命是无足轻重的\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}But that doesn't make us insignificant
Dialogue: 0,0:57:52.12,0:57:54.92,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,因为我们的觉醒 才有了对宇宙的认识\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}because we are the cosmos made conscious.
Dialogue: 0,0:57:54.92,0:57:59.76,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,从某种程度上讲 生命就是宇宙认知自我的过程\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}Life is the means by which the universe understands itself.
Dialogue: 0,0:58:02.40,0:58:06.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,在我看来 我们存在的意义恰恰在于\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}And, for me, our true significance lies in our ability
Dialogue: 0,0:58:06.40,0:58:12.40,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,我们对这个神奇宇宙的探索和认识的欲望\N{\fs13\fnHelvetica\fe0}and our desire to understand and explore this beautiful universe.
Dialogue: 0,0:58:20.48,0:58:28.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,# We have all the time in the world #
Dialogue: 0,0:58:20.48,0:58:25.48,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,{\an8\fad(300,300)\fs16\fn方正准圆简体\c&H26F4FF&\3c&H000000&\3a&H88&\bord2}（片尾曲：Amalia Gre- We Have All Time In The World）
Dialogue: 0,0:58:31.48,0:58:36.72,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,# Time enough for life to unfold #
Dialogue: 0,0:58:36.72,0:58:41.36,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,# All the precious things love has in store... #
Dialogue: 0,0:58:55.36,0:58:58.88,*Default,NTP,0000,0000,0000,,# Only now. #
